Hey.
Heat.
Hello, good evening and good day
everybody and welcome back to the Ask a
Budget show. Today we are doing episode
332. I hope you're all doing great. I'm
going to take questions that you all
have asked in the comments as many as of
those as I can. Uh but before we do
that, let's see who all is there on the
live stream. And before I do that, uh an
announcement that the next live stream
which is typically on Sundays, I'm going
to do it on Monday once again this time
because once again there is a cricket
match tomorrow and everybody is going to
watch that. So I don't want to compete
with with that with World Cup. I'm going
to do the next live stream on Monday at
8:00 p.m. India time. Okay, let's see
who is there on the live stream in the
live chat before we get going. Sagnik
Achara Katos Ary Vasi Shri Ramachandra
Namaste G thank you so much Sagnik
Acharia real
Jar Ram Geopolitical Dub is here from
Indor super beast USA is talking about
aliens Aditya Kulkarnney
um anonymous anonymous R7U5T
uh Adwit Ashini good evening Sam the
gamer hello good to see you really miss
Patel namaskar and shya to you ma'am.
Sam the gamer. Vault rook you
uh Jack Jack. Okay. I I saw what you did
there.
Uh who else do we have? Um pandemia
NPC without side quest. Hello
geopolitical your dad. Haha 77. Hello.
Good to see you. I'm good. How are you
doing? Somi is here from Jaipur. Uh Sam
the gamer Kedar Prabhu good evening
political once again. Vikash PJ
Manhattan I6W Abhishek Shukla down
Abhishek Shukla live talking about
tariff struck down. Tushar Kalborgi
hello good evening meet Raj Singh
Jadatama from Ahmedabad. Good to see
you. Good to see you sir. Uh Chetan
Aradhya Vikas PJ Crash and Rise Boswar
you dad once again. Aush Singh Aush
Singh is also here. Good evening sir.
Pranam fail namaskar ma'am somi Avin
Manhattan. Abishukal is here from Kpur.
All right. Chetan Ara NPC once again.
Manishar Roso. Namaste ma'am. Namaste.
Ready. Always ready. Good to have you.
Random skull. J Sri Krishna sir ita.
Hello Raguir Soleni from Varodra Visha
student doing doing exercise. Good to
see you. Shasitra is here from Moscow.
Good evening to you sir. Uh Amisha
Mishra good evening ma'am. N Shivias
good to see you. Good to see you.
Priyanka Javalia hello. Good evening
ma'am. Alvin Rodriguez good evening sir.
Vikash PJ says which match is it
tomorrow? It's India South Africa. I'm
sure lots of going people going to watch
want to watch it. So I will not do a
live stream tomorrow evening because
it's going to coincide exactly with that
match. Uh Ranjit KM RRI Danisha good
evening ma'am Villinay hello Arian Matei
hello Swami Swami says the DAO has hit
50K outstanding Montu Prajapati uh
Vikash PJ Ankitakab good evening ma'am
Chetan Aradia unknown gunman is saying
love from Pakistan will good to have you
online Mahadev Alvin Rodriguez once
again good evening M2CM
rider good evening online, Chhattan
Aradya and so many other people. It is
here from Toronto. Good morning, I
suppose. Good morning. Um,
Surya Pratab Vish July is here from
Canada.
Uh, hersan hers
hersan Mituka. Good evening. Good
evening and everyone else. I won't be
able to greet you all individually.
Sudir Kumar, good to see you. Mr. Nash
KK
Undisp
Namaste Karan Kumar and everyone else
Pratim Anupma from Bangalore
and everyone else. Okay. Okay. Let's get
going with some questions. What's the
first question I have picked? Let's see.
Okay. This is by Abhishek Shukla live.
The question is, "What are my views on
former US President Obama's latest
comments about aliens?
So, Mr. Obama in a recent podcast, I
believe uh with somebody was asked a
question about aliens. I mean, do aliens
exist or something like that. And Obama
said, "Yes, they exist, but I have never
seen them or something like that."
Something to that effect, right? So, he
kind of said that yes, they exist, but I
haven't seen them or I haven't seen any
evidence of them and so on. And then he
kind of clarified saying that, you know,
why do I say that they exist? because
the universe is so vast and there are so
many stars and planets so there's a high
probability they exist that's the kind
of uh logic or rational he gave but he
kind of said that they exist and then
later President Trump the current
president of the United States Donald
Trump was asked about this and he kind
of said that Obama should not reveal
such sort of the sort of classified
information which is interesting yeah
and then this is what the white house
tweeted recently so Trump has put this
uh this post on his social media uh
channel
uh and here's what it says. It says that
based on the tremendous interest shown,
I will be the directing the Secretary of
War and other relevant departments and
agencies to begin the process of
identifying and releasing government
files related to alien and
extraterrestrial life, unidentified
aerial phenomena, that is UAP and
unidentified flying objects, UFOs and
any and all other information connected
to these highly complex but extremely
interesting and important matters.
So that is what Trump has announced. So
it looks like Trump is going to have his
uh his his government release some
information about UFOs, UAPs, alien
life, extraterrestrial life and other
complex matters like Trump says. Now
what does this indicate?
Does it indicate that the US has been
has evidence of extraterrestrial life?
Does it indicate that the US government
has been contacted by aliens? Does it
mean that they they they
have evidence that aliens have visited
the earth? All these UFO reports and
sightings that we observe, do they mean
do they indicate that aliens actually
actively visit our planet? What's the
truth? Well, I suspect the truth is that
these aerial phenomena that we observe
that some people observe in some parts
of the world, they are most likely
highly advanced technology, classified
secret technology of the US government,
US military, DARPA, etc. That's what I
believe it is, right? Sounds, it looks
like UFOs or whatever, but maybe it's
just very advanced technology that is
secret and they're testing it out or
whatever. And sometimes people because
the human population is so so high
people sometimes notice this observe it
and sometimes they take videos. I
believe that's the most likely
explanation for these phenomena that are
observed sometimes
secret technology being tested or being
used. That's what I believe it is. I am
extremely skeptical about any claims by
anybody that aliens have visited our
planet or are in the process of uh
visiting our planet, right? And that the
US government has uh has had um you know
communication with aliens. Some people
claim that the US government is in is in
possession of the bodies of deceased
extraterrestrials. Some people claim
that the US government is in possession
of of alien technology and artifacts
like flying saucers, UFOs, whatever. I
am extremely highly tremendously
terribly frighteningly skeptic skeptical
about these claims. My view is that it's
all advanced technology that the
Americans are developing. The the the
technology that they are developing in
secret, it's typically 30 40 years ahead
of whatever we think is the most
advanced technology.
So I think that's the that's what it is.
and just to mislead the public so that
people don't realize how advanced their
actual technology is. You'll they'll
spin stories of UFOs and aliens and
extraterrestrials and all that. So that
is what I believe the case is. Do I
believe that alien life exists out
there? I'm pretty sure that
extraterrestrial life does exist in the
universe. The universe is just too vast.
There's way too many stars and planets
out there. 10 to 23 stars roughly, give
or take. I mean that's a tremendously
high number large number right so I am
pretty sure that extraterrestrial life
alien life does exist out there but I
don't think it's contacted us
because
the odds are just it doesn't make sense
statistically and why would the aliens
only contact the United States
government tell me why why are why are
these phenomena only visible over the
United States and Western Europe and so
on why is that so Right. Um but the
question then arises why is Trump saying
that he's going to release information
or direct his minions to release
information about all these matters?
Well, one explanation
plausible explanation is that the
release of such such information
typically follows the same pattern as
the Epstein files release. lots of
redactions, lots of documents will be
redacted and the most important and key
information will be blacked out and it
will create this buzz
across the world. Everyone's going to
start obsessing about aliens and UFOs
and that can serve as a smoke screen to
draw attention away from what's really
important in the world. Maybe the US
intends to invade Iran. Maybe that's a
good time to release such information.
Maybe there's something else that the
Americans are planning and to divert the
world's attention away from what they're
planning, they'll release such
information which would be typically
significantly redacted and you won't
really, you know, get the juicy parts.
So that's how I see it. I don't take
this very seriously. I have I mean since
I was a kid, I've been super interested
in aliens and UFOs, right?
But I have never seen any piece of hard
unambiguous evidence that convinces me
that we have been visited by
extraterrestrials in the past or that we
we are currently being visited. I have
seen no evidence that convinces me of
that. So that's that's my view on this
matter. I don't think even if Trump has
this released, I don't think we're going
to get any hard unambiguous evidence of
uh what we are seeking. Maybe you will
see claims that the government
government of the US has been has
contacted has been contacted by aliens.
But uh will we see evidence of that? We
won't see evidence. We'll see files in
which claims are made.
But that's just claims on paper. Where's
the actual evidence? A document released
by the government of any country is
simply a claim. The evidence show us an
alien or show us an a recording that
genuinely proves you know, whether it's
a video recording or photographic
evidence or whatever that genuinely
unambiguously proves that these contacts
have happened that I think is is highly
unlikely. So, let's wait and watch. I am
super skeptical about this. I would love
to believe I would love I mean I I'll be
the happiest person
if this actually is proven that aliens
are real and they have visited the
earth. I'll be super pleased if to to
know that if it if it is genuinely
unambiguously provable but until this
happens I am super skeptical. So let's
wait and watch.
Okay, a bunch of questions about the
recent AI summit. Aayush Singh says the
recent AI summit. What's my opinion on
that? Where does India stand in the AI
race? Rushab says how do you see the AI
summit in India keeping the Galotas
fiasco aside the bashini AI was
introduced which can be used as
translation tools for Indian languages
without changing voice server is
constantly outperforming on various
tests and it will be building it will
now be building our LLM like chat GP
perplexity etc so what tangible outcomes
do you see from the summit for our AI
goals and mission really now Miss Patel
says so that one Chinese robot from a
shady university go out all the media
coverage while there were literally tens
of other companies who had their 100%
Indian robotic dogs. Of course, people
take advantage of uh you know one out of
100 negative things and one blot is all
that's needed on a white sheet but there
were some really awesome things at the
AI summit and the common man and women
were interested as showed in the
attendance at Serb's venue. There were
more people than the entire attendance
of the 2023 2025 Paris AI summit.
Look, first of all, the Indian public is
very interested in AI, right? Lots of
Indians are are full-scale adopters of
AI. They use AI for everything. There's
a tremendous amount of interest in India
towards AI. And whenever there is some
kind of success story that emanates out
of India like the servum AI success
story, Indians are drawn to that.
Indians want to see India succeed.
There is no question about it. Indians
are desperate to see India succeed and
when something like servi comes out it's
it's great news for India right and I'm
sure there are lots of other companies
that have been doing tremendous work and
much of that must have been showcased at
the AI summit now I did not visit the AI
summit I did not participate I didn't I
did not visit uh but I hear good things
also from the AI summit now let's set
that fiasco aside for a moment that
robot dog and that uh drone football or
whatever from that one university let's
not discuss that the question really is
where does India stand in the AI race uh
what are India's AI goals
what is India's AI mission does India
even have an AI mission right so
does India have AI goals we the prime
minister uh gave uh you know an address
he gave a speech he speaks about
sovereign AI he speaks about uh ethical
AI and all that uh that's all Right.
That's okay. Fantastic. The you know
sovereign AI for India and ethical AI
which will be inclusive and know all
those buzzwords and whatnot. And he also
said that India is going to be an AI
superpower by 2047. That's what the
prime minister said. Fantastic.
What are the facts? Where does the world
really stand today in terms of the AI
race and where is India's position in
that?
See, when it comes to AI superpower by
2047,
to be very honest, the race for AI
superpowered them is going to
essentially end by 2040 20 27 28. By
2030, one nation will win. Forget about
2047. This is not mech mechanical
engineering. This is the air race. All
the timelines, time frames are super
compressed and the more time goes, the
more compressed these these milestones
become. AI progress milestones, right?
2047 is like talking about the 25th
century. Essentially, the AI race will
be won or lost by 2030 latest.
Now, where does India stand? that we
have various companies in the world
mainly the US companies uh open AI,
Anthropic, XAI,
uh Google AI, Gemini and they have these
products like the chat bots like chat
JPT they've got nano banana that's a
Google product um there is uh what are
the various things uh there is the there
are various video generation tools super
powerful video generation tools there
are uh
So we we have French companies too like
Mistal. We have open AI. We have we have
the Chinese companies like uh uh
Deepseek. Deepseek is is a great example
of a Chinese company, right? We have
Quinn of Alibaba. We have Kimi which is
Chinese. We have a bunch of European uh
you know options out there. Um
and and there's a tremendous amount of
progress that's been made. Now when it
comes to the American companies, they
have invested hundreds of billions of
dollars
into the AI race into developing the
products and now they're they're coming
out with new models every few months
almost every few weeks. Now the
timelines time frames are getting
compressed. Now where does India stand
is the main question. Now let's talk
about what is it that is the fuel for
AI. What is the fuel of AI? H it's data.
The fuel of AI is data. Now where do
these companies like chat GPD open air
etc anthropic and so on where do they
get the data from? First of all from all
the social media platforms that the
Americans own American social media
platforms on which our data is hosted
Indian data a lot of tremendous amount
of Indian data is hosted on American
social media platforms then you have
platforms like Amazon and whatnot right
so data is the currency it's the fuel of
AI
that that's one way the American
companies have built their AI they've
trained their AI on this data they
they've also scraped the entire internet
scraping of internet uh downloading
terabytes, hundreds of terabytes of
torrent which is illegal obviously you
know but whatever
now if you want to see where India
stands let's compare with China let's
not compare with the US let's not even
think of comparing India with the US
let's compare India with China so what
is the Chinese model of AI development
so China has this strategy called
sovereign internet you know the great
fire firewall of China it uh it's like a
Wald garden and Chinese citizens are not
allowed to access external uh you know
platforms like Google and whatnot. So
the Chinese have their sovereign
internet strategy. They have their
domestic platforms like BU like Tik Tok
like WeChat and so on. And this has
ensured that all the data of the Chinese
citizens 1.4 billion Chinese citizens
has remained closed off to the world.
Okay. What kind of data? Behavioral
data, cultural data, linguistic data,
sociological data, anthropological data,
all the patterns, all the everything,
all of that, all the Chinese data is
closed off. It is it is walled, it is
walled off from the world, right? So
this has given the Chinese a huge
massive
data set of Chinese data for trading
indigenous Chinese models.
That's the that's the Chinese way of
doing things. Now, let's compare that
with the Indian way of doing things.
India's data.
Well, the American platforms have
complete access to Indian data. What
kind of platforms? Google, Amazon, Meta
and so on. They have free access to
Indian data. India has essentially
exported away all of its vital
national data
to these American platforms in exchange
for what? In exchange for free services.
H So India's data now is American data.
They own it and they're exploiting it.
Our data is now in the hands of the
Americans. China has data sovereignty.
India is
a data vasal.
India is a data colony. Right? So that's
one huge problem India has. Understand
this. Now I could say everything is
hunky dory and everything is fine. We
will show the world. But that's not the
truth. I won't I won't lie to you.
Right? I have to be honest with you. The
second issue is this.
We have all these Indian startups,
right? Saram is a great example. We we
have a bunch of other startups. We also
have a a lot of academic researchers who
were doing uh research in AI. So what
kind of models
AI models are the Indian startups and
Indian academic researchers using? They
typically are using
Chinese open-source models like the ones
I mentioned, you know, Deepseek and uh
Kim and Quen and whatnot. These models,
they are very good models. they they are
almost equivalent to chat GPD or
whatever or or claude anthropic they
give the same level of of performance
for a fraction of the cost.
So India startups and academics whatever
they're building they are building on
top of these Chinese models on top of
these Chinese opensource weights.
So let's take the example of Serbam. It
is India's most serious uh AI model.
It's the it's the yeah the most serious
Indian effort thus far, right? AI
effort. So
the company has trained its data its AI
from scratch. So there is excellent
excellent execution, excellent
engineering, no question about it. The
problem is this. When it comes to
servers AI, the architecture
is open source. It is not serv's
proprietary
homegrown architecture, home design
architecture. It's open-source
architecture. It's open source
architecture applied to Indian languages
like Hindi and uh um you know Marathi
and Tamil and BJPUI and and whatnot. So
we're training on local data with open
source architecture. Let me explain what
that means. Let me give you an analogy.
Okay? So, imagine you are running a
restaurant.
You're running a restaurant. Imagine.
And you're using a classic, openly
published cookbook. Somebody has
published a cookbook. It's a great
fantastic cookbook, best in the world,
and it's available to everybody for
free. So, you take that cookbook and you
use it for running your restaurant. Your
cookbook,
your your restaurant is your AI. Let's
say your cookbook is your open-source
architecture.
So the cookbook is open to everybody
which means everybody can see the
recipes, everybody can see the
techniques,
you can use that but you as long as you
keep using that you are not inventing
any new cooking methods. Right? So your
local data is the specific ingredients
you use in your country and the customer
tastes in your city. What are the local
spices? What do your regular customers
like? What do they complain about?
That's your local data. Now, how do you
train the system? You gradually, slowly,
iteratively tweak how much salt, how
much spice, how much seasoning do you
add? What are the portion sizes? H,
what's the best menu selection that is
best tailored and best suited for your
clients? Right? So that's that way you
can tweak the system but you are never
create you don't create a fundamentally
unique new cuisine or new cooking style
right so this setup is like a chef who
strictly follows a well-known cookbook
and uh and optimizes every dish
to his own neighborhood's tastes.
So the chef is highly trained, very
competent guy and he has very
competently adapted the cookbook to the
local context. But there is zero
culinary in innovation. There is no
innovation. There is no invention.
You're simply taking somebody else's
architecture, you fine-tuning it
uh based on your local data set. This is
not novelty. This is not innovation. So
if this is what India calls sovereign AI
then every nation is running their own
sovereign AI now right so my point is
serv is fantastic serv needs to be
applauded that's how you begin that's
how you begin playing the game you start
by copying what others do adapting
taking their architecture taking their
methodology and and using it and
fine-tuning it but eventually we have to
start creating our own cuisine Right. We
have not reached there yet. Serv is
fantastic. Tremendous execution,
tremendous engineering, etc., etc., etc.
Great job. I am not for one second
criticizing Saram. I am just taking it
as an example of where a nation like
India needs to begin. That's how we
start. Before we learn how to fly, we
need to learn how to walk, then to jog,
then to run and so on. So, right now, we
are somewhere between walking and
jogging. Okay.
Now
the fact that you now hopefully
understand is that China is doing
indigenous frontier research and India
is doing adaptation of open-source AI
systems open source AI architecture
right the other issue is that China is
spending about almost 2 and a half% of
its GDP
on on on reverse on research and
development okay China is spending 2.5%
of its GDP on research and development
R&D and China has essentially reversed
all the brain drain issues it faced.
India is spending less than 1%. It's
spending about 0.7% of its GDP on R&D
and I wonder what that R&D quality also
is knowing the Indian universities right
and India India ensures that the best
talent that it has leaves and serves
other countries. So the question is is
this how India becomes an AI superpower
by 2047? That's the question right now.
There are other issues. Now when it when
it comes to this AI summit okay it went
off went off and all now there is this
really interesting uh thing that
happened give me a okay okay right uh
let me put this on the screen I don't
want to play the video
so here's an interesting uh
thing that came out of the AI summit uh
Sriam Krishnan senior white house policy
advisor on artificial intelligence he
said that we want to make sure that the
world uses the American AI stack we also
want the world to use our AI model. We
want all our allies which means vasals
including India to leverage our AI
infrastructure which means don't develop
your own indigenous AI infrastructure
use our AI infrastructure give us your
data we will do everything you simply
use our AI infrastructure so the
American companies have been essentially
mining
the Indian public's personal data right
and they have been training American air
platforms on it that's how chat GPT and
all these other chat box chat bots that
speak Hindi and other Indian languages
right that's how they've done it so the
Americans want to continue doing this
and in exchange for that India's IT
firms will continue to receive American
contracts
the problem the government of India
faces is that you know IT is is fading
now with the advent of AI who wants to
outsource it to to India right so we and
And you know the Indian government has
failed to reform and diversify the the
the economy of India. Where's the
manufacturing? Where's the
diversification? It's all dependent even
now on it. So if it dies, it's a
disaster for India. So India, the
government of India now in the short
term needs to somehow keep the IT IT
industry alive.
We need the Indian IT firms to continue
to receive American contracts. We can't
allow the government of India can't
allow the IT exports
to die because we don't have a sound
manufacturing base. We don't have a
massive manufacturing base and it's the
IT the money we receive from it is one
of India's biggest sources of income and
if that goes away in the next 2 3 years
it's a disaster for India. So to prevent
this we should have worked really hard
in the past 10 11 12 15 years to to set
up a major massive manufacturing base.
We haven't done that. we haven't
diversified the Indian uh you know
India's India's economy. So that's where
we are. So that's the leverage the
Americans have on India and the
Americans will will essentially you know
buy stakes in various companies right
companies that make sovereign AI systems
large language models and by taking
ownership or part partial ownership of
these Indian companies they will control
the little innovation that India makes
and by controlling the AI stack like
Sriam Krishna says they will gain
control of our of our economy Right. And
this will give them even more leverage
over India and obviously this will then
be used on to to influence and perhaps
direct India's foreign policy, domestic
policy and so on. Right? So that is the
situation. That's where India stands in
AI. I
cannot lie to you and say everything is
fantastic and everything is wonderful.
We're going to be AI superpower by 47.
is doesn't matter the race is still 2030
only even that will be too late possibly
the AI race will be won in the next 2
three years one or lost where is India
in this
India is taking baby steps right now so
I'm I'm very glad to see what server AI
is doing and other AI startups are doing
but we've also had all these rocket
startups in India
Right. Space startups, what are they
doing now? What happened?
You know, it's it's
yeah. So that's where we stand in AI.
Does India where does India stand in the
race in the AI race? India is not really
participating in the AI race right now.
And that's why when you're not
participating,
you talk about ethical AI blah blah blah
blah blah all that stuff. AI is a tool.
It's like saying we need ethical swords
and ethical ethical AK-47s
and ethical Brahmos missiles.
Technology is technology. It can be used
for good or evil. When we are not
developing the technology, we are not
leading the race. We are lecturing the
world that we need ethical AI that there
need to be more ethical. AI is a tool in
the and whoever is at the forefront of
AI development will use that to win the
geopolitical race.
And the ones who are on the sidelines
will say ethically ethically that's
where India is right now. That is the
honest truth. A lot of you may say that
I'm being blackpilled and I'm
blackpilling you or whatever. I can only
tell you the truth the way I see it.
Maybe other people may see some other
truth. You can listen to them also.
Don't simply rely on my opinion. Listen
to other people. Take a 360°ree
perspective and then form your own
opinion based on the best judgment that
you have. The way I see it, India is not
participating in the air race. Yeah.
Amisha Mishra says India's AI summit
2026 has sparked global out debate after
a major controversy involving a robot
dog showcased as Indian in a certain
university. But it's clear that the that
the robot dog was Chinese. Does India
have a real indigenous robotic dog
technological
technology manufacturing or whatever and
AI innovations? How does it impact
India's global technological image? Is
it an international embarrassment?
Napoleon Singh Shikawad says whenever
there's hope of coming out of some
something positive coming out from
India, somebody messes up badly this
particular university at the AI summit.
So what's the deal?
So there is this one university, right?
And in this AI summit, they messed up
very badly. There is this uh person who
was not even an AI expert or an AI
professor who was a professor of some
god knows what other subject who comes
as the spokesperson representative of
the university talking about AI which
the person clearly knows nothing about
and then claims that this robot dog is
purely indigenously developed in their
university
by their students through their center
of excellence or something like that.
And there was some other football drone
thing also that they had. They said even
that is developed by them. And clearly
these are shelf bought products. You can
you can look it up online how much it
costs to buy it. And this obviously has
given India's enemies a field day on
social media and in the media overall
you know disparaging India and so on. So
why does such a thing happen and what
action should be taken?
See if if you are a serious country and
if this sort of international
embarrassment happens
you will first of all ensure that this
person who has caused the embarrassment
their academic career is over.
It it has to be like that. But in the
case of this individual nothing will
happen. That person will probably become
a star now.
And when a university causes okay that's
about the person that that one person
right and when a university causes such
a horrible embarrassment for the country
that university should be drecognized
and should be penalized very heavily and
made an example of so that nobody else
does it again but once again nothing
will happen because this is India India
is not a serious country
India is not a serious country
and this what we have seen happen it's
simply a symptom of the actual disease.
The disease is the rot and the
corruption in India's academic system,
educational system. India's education
system is garbage. It is trash.
That's not how you become Vishwaguru by
having a trashy garbage-like education
system. The majority see I'll tell first
of all before I say that there are some
good professors
and academics in India. there there
probably are some worldclass professors
and academics and in India and probably
there must be some in institutions or
universities that are world class
possibly
okay so whatever I'm going to say
doesn't apply to everybody
there are exceptions but the
overwhelming majority of India's
professors
okay
they they're rubbish they're rubbish
incompetent
They publish some rubbish papers every
year. What they do at the higher levels
in academia. They will have a bunch of
students who work under them. Okay?
They'll make the students do all the
work and then they will steal the
credit. When the paper is published, the
professor's name will be at the front,
the first author, the primary author.
The student if he or she is lucky will
be second, third author or whatever.
Often the students don't even get any
credit. These professors do nothing.
Absolutely nothing.
They're parasites and that's the norm
across Indian academia. That's the norm.
Okay. It's a highly highly corrupt
system. There must be some exceptions
but overall it's a highly corrupt
system.
What innovation happens in India? What
research is done in India's academic
institutions? Nothing. publishing trashy
papers three, four, five, whatever per
year,
rehashing some old nonsense. It's not
research, it's not innovation.
Until this core the these set of core
issues, unless until you fix them,
you're going to keep on getting such
such you know such embarrass
embarrassing incidents
that embarrass Indian in front of the
world. What you have seen is not an
exception. What you have seen is a
symptom of something that exists all
across Indian academia
and that's why I've been saying for
years that India needs to reform the
education system
right this is going to continue this is
exactly what happens all over the place
and you see that person that that
individual who was talking about AI that
person was not even some a person with
any background in AI and they they
become the face of everything they take
all the it and that's that's the norm in
Indian academia that's the norm and
that's why India has this problem of
brain drain everybody who is worth
anything wants to leave the country can
you blame them for this now who's to
blame for this
do you blame the universities do you
blame the teachers the the the
professors the academics no part of the
system the system is designed to serve
them who do you blame You blame the
government of India who are doing
nothing about this. They know exactly
what the situation is. They are doing
nothing about this.
So,
so what you have seen this robot dog
incident, it is not the disease. It is a
symptom of the disease. And the disease
is not being treated, is not being
treated. The disease is being fed and
it's becoming larger. It's becoming
stronger.
That is the truth.
Okay, let's talk about Iran. Rushabare
says, "What's the deal with Iran? Iran
and the US are making conflicting
statements. Trump is desperate." Okay,
if you say so. The USS Gerald Ford is
now coming in. Yeah, it's it's crossed.
It's in the Mediterranean or about to
enter the Red Sea or wherever. So it's
going to reach the uh you know
the western Indian Ocean region or maybe
near the US kind of near the Porsche
Gulf or whatever right is the US
implying a troa strategy of creating
chaos with Iran within Iran by creating
spillover of what happened in Syria plus
US attacking itself and a complete
isolation of Iran by every means
including economy and diplomacy. Will
there be a war or is war inevitable?
Aayush Singh says the warning to Iran
and a 10-day time limit given by Trump
to make a deal or face military action.
Recent buildups indicate the US is
preparing for war. What lies in the
future? Recent developments suggest that
a war between the US and Iran is
inevitable. Question mark. What will be
its implications and how tough will it
be for the US to take down Iran? So
Trump has said that he has given Iran
maybe a 10day deadline or something to
accept all America's conditions.
The Americans obviously have imposed a
set of conditions on Iran. These are
obviously maximalist demands. Iran must
stop uh completely dismantle and roll
back its uh nuclear program. That's
number one. And secondly, the Americans
must get complete control of Iran's oil,
Iran's oil export. So the Americans
decide who gets it and who doesn't get
it. And so on and so forth. There'll be
a whole list of other demands as well.
So essentially it's about turning Iran
into a vasal into a slave of the US.
Right? The US decides what Iran does and
what Iran doesn't do and Iran should be
in a position where it can't defend
itself. That's what the US wants and
Iran obviously will not accept that Iran
has you know pushed back for more than
40 years. Do you think they will now
give in to what the Americans are
demanding? The US and Israel essentially
right. So uh there's a round of
negotiations, diplomatic talks that's
happening between the US and Iran right
now
um DHA Qatar most likely right and in
the meanwhile the Americans are
assembling a massive military presence
in the West Asia region and beyond
surrounding region massive military
buildup is happening right now. There's
already one aircraft carrier strike
group in the region. It's not just one
aircraft carrier. It's a whole bunch of
ships around the aircraft carrier that
are already deployed. And the second
one, USS Gerald Ford, is now also moving
in. Whether it enters the Red Sea or not
remains to be seen. Maybe it'll just
remain stationed west of the coast of
Israel. That's also a possibility to
defend Israel. Um, and a lot of military
movement has happened and is already is
al is even now happening. lots of um you
know transport aircraft and whatn not
coming in from Europe and from the
United States in the region around uh
Iran. So it looks like the US is is
creating a posture military posture that
can enable it to strike at Iran if
required and strike pretty heavily at
Iran.
So that why is this being done is the
question. Is this an indication that the
US is now imminently going to attack
Iran?
Maybe not necessarily.
See, when you are
when you are negotiating with somebody,
you want leverage. Now, if your troops
in your aircraft carriers and everything
is far away, then the guy you are
negotiating with is not going to be
really scared of you. But if you bring
in all the all the military force and
surround
your negotiating partner, then they will
feel the heat and then they'll be more
likely to break under the strain and
give in to your demands. So, diplomacy
is a continuation of war by other means,
right? Diplomacy is war by other means.
So, to succeed in diplomacy, you have to
use leverage. All kinds of leverage. I'm
twisting, right? I'm twisting. So, how
do you twist arm? By arms? by by by
you know threatening them with military
force and and destruction and you can
threaten them only when you have the
military in place around the nation. So
what are the possibilities?
One possibility is that the US
successfully uses its its military
leverage
to make Iran capitulate and give it what
it wants. So then one option, one
possibility is that Iran accepts all the
American demands and the American
military then partially moves out and
Iran becomes a US wasal. But that will
be disastrous for Iran because uh then
the government of Iran will no longer be
seen as legitimate even by the people
who support it. So that doesn't make
sense. So it doesn't make sense for Iran
to uh to cave in to give into the US
demands. So the second option is Iran
does not accept American demands or the
key demands
which will give the US
the option of either invading
a full-scale invasion or a series of
strikes, decapitation strikes to take
out the top leadership of Iran
which obviously is military conflict and
military conflict is not that easy to to
do against Iran because Iran has see
Iran doesn't have a great air force but
Iran is a very very capable missile
force. They probably have tens of
thousands of missiles in their
stockpile. They were able to essentially
overwhelm Israel's air defense right in
the 12-day war last year. And if there's
a full-scale invasion on Iran of Iran or
a massive um attack on Iran, that Iran
is fully capable of taking out the US
air bases and military bases in the
region in the in the West Asia region.
Iran is also cap capable of blockading
the straight of Hormuz. India is also
Iran is also capable of uh destroying a
lot of the oil and gas infrastructure in
West Asia. You know Saudi
infrastructure, Iraqi infrastructure,
Kuwaiti infrastructure and so on and
other nations and that's why a lot of
these nations in the region don't want a
war between the US, Israel and Iran. Uh
but
Trump he's already gambled it looks like
looks like he see when you move so much
equipment so much manpower etc
across continents that's very very
expensive.
So you don't do it just to simply
pressurize someone,
right? It's already a gamble. You've
already spent so much money, so much of
your nation's money to bring in this
enormous force posture in West Asia.
So maybe Trump is
Trump may possibly has calculated that
if Iran doesn't give in to the US
demands, all of them, he's going to
attack them. So if he attacks them, what
happens? Well, it's not going to be easy
to defeat Iran. Like I said, Iran can
unleash tremendous destruction in the
nations surrounding it and also on on on
the US military. Uh unless the Americans
plan and time their attacks in such a
way that Iran is completely crippled
before something happens, which is
easier said than done. So they can take
out Iran's radars, air defense systems,
and so on and make you know that sort of
thing. But still Iran can fight back.
See when it comes to great example is
like what somebody asked last time the
Houthis right Houthis in Yemen the
Houthi the Americans have been trying to
fight the Houthis from 2024 until now.
The Houthis had blockaded the Red Sea
right the the straight of Babal Mandib
and they bombarded the Houthis. They
launched hundreds of air strikes from
the Houthis and the Houthis are still
there. Of course they have been depleted
and they have been their their
capabilities have been hurt but they're
still there. They're still fighting. And
then eventually the Houthies accepted
the American demand to allow American
ships to to transit across the state of
Babl Babal Mandib. But the Houthis said
Israeli ships will not be allowed and
the Americans couldn't force them. So
despite launching hundreds of air
strikes on the Houthis, they have been
able to defeat the Houthis. The Houthis
are in a small nation called Yemen,
relatively small nation called Yemen.
Iran is gigantic. So it's not easy to
defeat Iran. The easiest thing to do is
to to do decapitation strikes, take out
the top leadership if possible, take out
the the nuclear program, but even then
Iran may fight. Iran may keep fighting.
So if the US is not able to defeat Iran
within a week or two, it it could become
a long drawn out war. And you see
there's other factors too. There's other
factors too. Let me show you. Let just
you know what what are the other
factors? Let's take a look at the map.
The map will show you the other factors.
See,
Russia and China both need Iran to
survive. Okay. Now, when it comes to
Iran, is Russia far away? The Iran is a
few kilometers, maybe couple of a couple
of maybe 100 or so kilometers from the
Caspian Sea, right? What's north of the
Caspian Sea? It's Russia, right? It's
Russia. Russia isn't that far away.
So the Russians could come to Thran's
aid in some some way or the other. See,
China doesn't want a military
confrontation with the US. China is
afraid of that. The Russians not so
much. The Russians are hard retaliators.
They already fighting the US in this
Ukraine proxy war. Right? So Russia may
not allow Iran to just roll over, right?
Even if Iran is going down, they may
resupply Iran and and keep them and keep
them going. So just the the same way
that the that when Russia invaded
Ukraine,
the West, which is Western Europe, which
is a proxy of the US, is keeping Ukraine
going on by supplying it with money,
arms, ammunition, all that. The same way
Russia could start supplying Ukraine,
sorry, Iran with whatever it needs to
keep going in a war against the US. If
that happens, it could become a Vietnam
style disaster for the US if if it's
possible. It's not that easy. Obviously,
Russia is already embroiled in Ukraine.
Now, does it want to get embroiled in in
another war as well?
That could seriously affect Russia's
position in Ukraine.
So, there's a lot of factors in here.
Even the Chinese factor is there. The
Chinese could possibly try and resupply
Iran with weapons possibly.
So, there's a lot of factors in here.
The Americans obviously will not sit
back and just watch this happen. They
will take some action. But yeah, this
could soon become a major conflration if
the Americans aren't able to defeat Iran
rapidly,
right? And it's not easy to defeat Iran
rapidly. It's not easy. Eventually, the
US, I I would say, will probably win
because they're just way too powerful.
But if Russia gets involved, if China
gets involved, then it may become super
complicated.
And Russia is not far. Russia can
directly supply Iran if uh it needs.
So yeah, it looks like something is
going to go down like people say. Yeah,
looks like uh a war could happen soon.
Trump is saying 10 days maybe. Who
knows? I I hope there's no war
obviously. I hope there is no war, but
it looks like a war could happen in by
this weekend or by next weekend. It
looks like that. I hope it doesn't
happen, but the possibility is very high
right now.
Real Vadir Putin says do you think after
a regime change in Iran if that succeeds
if this happens will can India and China
come closer? Do you think if India and
China come come closer without India
being becoming powerful the relationship
will be dominated by China.
Okay. So if let's say there is a war
between the US and Iran, the US invades
Iran and eventually the US is able to
defeat Iran, carry out a regime change
and put a puppet government in place in
Thran. H so Iran Iran becomes a US vasal
again like it was before 1979
and uh all that happens
and Iran and Pakistan are then obviously
both US vasals. they can both be used by
the US against India that sort of thing
and China loses its great strategic
asset and partnership which is Iran. So
China becomes more isolated
in this scenario. Do you think do I
think that India and China can come
closer and become better friends or
something? Is it possible?
What do I think? I think it's highly
unlikely.
See,
at this point in time, India is being
asked by the US to make a choice.
Right now, India is being asked to make
a choice. Trump hasn't said anything in
public, but India is being asked to make
a choice by the Americans. You either
come on our side or we will treat you as
an enemy. We'll destroy you.
I don't think India has too much of a
choice in this matter.
strategic autonomy and all we can keep
on doing that that game of balancing
tightroppe walking and all that you know
be the bridge between east and west be
friends with Russia be friends with the
US be friends with the Europe and so on
but the Americans don't want India to
play that game the Americans are giving
India simple choice you either come on
our side or we're going to treat you as
the enemy just like we treat Russia and
China we're going to destroy you
that's one factor
and India right now is probably making
some kind of choice
right now. Now let's say India remains
strategically autonomous.
In that case, could India come closer to
China or could China and India get
closer together? Uh in my opinion, India
and China cannot become close closer
unless the core issue is resolved. The
core issue is the undemarcated India
Tibet border. That has to be resolved.
that has to be demarcated. As long as
that is not demarcated, India simply
can't trust China.
Simply cannot trust China.
The Chinese are on the one hand are
building up their infrastructure,
military infrastructure north of the
line of actual control in Tibetan
territory, right? On the other hand,
they'll come and say, "H, we want to be
friends." How does that work?
We have this massive trade imbalance
between India and China. There's so many
issues,
right? I think it's highly unlikely that
India and China will come closer.
Nothing substantial will happen
in terms of closeness
until the core issue is resolved. The
core issue is the border. Chinese have
steadfastly refused to demarcate the
border. They want to keep the border
open undemarcated so that they can keep
on using that as a pressure point on
India.
So as long as they have this approach
their attitude this attitude towards
India things are not going to work out
between India and China.
So that is the situation. I don't see
this happening. I don't see it
happening.
Nirvana Shank says, "In response to the
Supreme Court of the US ruling,
President Trump stated to show you how
ridiculous the opinion is, the court
said, I am not allowed to charge even $1
to any country under EPA, but I'm
allowed to cut off any and all trade of
or business with the same country, even
imposing a foreign country destroying
embargo and do anything else I want to
do to them." How nonsensical is that? So
Trump is complaining about this Supreme
Court judgment. Okay. In light of this
statement and what's happened and his
indication that he might use other
statutory authorities to maintain
existing tariffs or impose an additional
10% levy. How should India interpret the
implications for US India US trade
policy stability, India's negotiating
leverage and the broader India US China
strategic and economic confrontation.
Okay. So Trump imposed a massive slab of
tariffs on essentially every country
last year, the liberation day tariffs or
whatever he called it, right? Um and he
did did this under the EA, the
International Emergency Economic Powers
Act, which is an act that was uh that
came into force came into existence in
1977. This EA gives the US president
authority to regulate certain
international economic transactions
after declaring a national emergency.
So he has to first declare a national
emergency and then he can use the EPA to
regulate various transactions with
various countries. So when can a
president invoke
EA? First he must declare a national
emergency. Second he must identify
explicitly some kind of unusual and
extraordinary threat to the United
States. Third he has to establish that
this threat has a foreign source. It can
be a threat related to national security
or foreign policy or the economy. Right?
So these are the conditions that have to
be satisfied before a a president can
use EPA. And if the president uses IEPA
then you can freeze foreignowned assets
of some other country or some individual
in the US. You can block financial
transactions. You can restrict trade and
investment through tariffs and prohibit
currency transfers and do all these
things. Okay. So that is EA. So the US
Supreme Court it has now ruled it has
said that these broad global tariffs
cannot be justified
by invoking emergency powers without
clear stat statutory backing. So
essentially it has said that these
tariffs okay that that Trump has invoke
imposed on all these countries these are
illegal.
That's what it has the Supreme Court of
the US has said.
So Trump is now in the process of
essentially dismantling rolling back
these tariffs. Doesn't work. But he has
signed an executive order. Uh so he has
signed an order ending these tariffs.
And he has also signed a different
executive order imposing a 10 10% tariff
on imports from all countries. It's a
blanket blanket tariff on every country
in the world 10%.
Okay. And this new tariff is being uh
imposed on under it's being enacted
under a different section section 122 of
some other trade act or something like
that. Okay. So it's a this this allows
the US president to impose temporary
tariffs for up to 150 days and any
extension of such tariffs will require
congressional approval.
So that is a stop gap situ solution.
Trump has found 10% tariffs on every
country in the world which will
eventually require approval from the
Congress. But he is now actively looking
for alternative tools that are faster
than going back to Congress and tools
that will allow him to once again start
imposing tariffs on other countries. You
know arbitrary tariffs like he has done.
So what we what we understand is that
the Trump regime remains protectionist.
Okay. it remains willing to use tariffs
as a structural instrument not as a last
resort bargaining chip.
So going forward it looks like the form
the form of the tariffs will be more
constrained that way it will be more
predictable and if he goes beyond that
you know US citizens and law firms can
once again litigate against him right
but the frequency of these tariffs and
the intensity of these unilaterally move
unilateral moves is likely to to to
decrease right so that's what's happened
that that's the Supreme Court ruling
that's what it actually means means now
does this mean that the that the United
States the structural decoupling it has
done from China does it is it reversed
now it doesn't mean that at all there
are other tariffs export controls and
advanced semiconductors um um investment
screening mechanisms all these things
remain intact and they are essentially
separate legally conceptually etc from
the EA issue so the US remains
structurally decoupled from China and
Trump immediately imposing this global
blanket 10% tariff. This tells you that
the Trump administration views tariffs,
it continues to view tariffs as a
central strategic instrument for them.
They will not let legal setbacks like
the Supreme Court ruling dilute their
micro strategy, their macro strategy
visa with China. And now they will look
for ways of of of
using the same tools under different
laws. So find the appropriate right laws
that exist in the US uh law book and use
the laws that are still applicable to
reimpose tariffs and and continue the
strategic decoupling from China.
Now we have to understand that you know
the these
tariffs when they're used against
American allies they obviously cause
collateral damage to American allies and
partners which obviously is a problem
when you're trying to build a coalition
against China against Beijing. Many
European nations are trying to once
again partner with Beijing because of
the tariffs that the Trump
administration has imposed on them
arbitrarily and pretty cruy. Right? So
what Nirvana Shanks is then asking is
about India. What what is India's
position situation in all all of this?
Does India have any negotiating leverage
and so on. So we have to remember that
India is not in the same category as
China or the US. India is nothing
compared to China. I mean India is not
as powerful as China. India is not that
big of an economy as China. And the US
continues to essentially frame India as
a strategic partner. Right? and they
want to use India as an essential
component
of their supply chain diversification
away from China in fields like
electronics and pharmaceuticals,
critical minerals,
um packs, silica, you know, all of that.
So India needs to assume
not short-term but medium-term that the
US tariffs will remain elevated by
historical standards. In the past there
used to be like 3% 4% 5% tariffs now
they're going to remain elevated at
least for the medium term not short-term
medium term maybe 3 to 5 years at least.
Yeah. And India should understand that
these legal constraints that the US
administration is facing they don't
remain they don't they don't remove
they don't change Trump's approach and
his attitude
towards the world okay he's going to
find other means of of achieving what he
wants to achieve India should understand
and realize that the China challenge
ensures the US see the US is facing the
China challenge China has risen and the
US wants to essentially isolate China
and and cut China down to size. In the
US is worried about China's
technological rise. Right? So this is
the China challenge that the US faces
and this ensures the US continues to
differentiate between China and nations
it can use more more profitably. Right?
So in the meanwhile India should should
build should diversify obviously you
know India should sign FTAs with as many
nations as possible including EU which
we've done the UK we've done Australia
we've done UAE do more do Canada do do
wherever else possible so we need to
diversify these are called buffers India
should find buffers right um and we have
to assume that in the future Trump may
throw another tantrum and you could once
again and he could once again repric
access to the US market on short notice.
tomorrow morning wake up and impose find
some new way of imposing tariffs and
tariffs once again go back to 20% 25 god
knows what right so we have to assume
this will happen again it's possible um
so and also India should also try and uh
try and use this as leverage against the
against the Trump administration this
ruling of the Supreme Court you know
India should push for maybe
maybe some kind of
modified amended free trade trade trade
agreement or arrangements that are
specific to specific sectors right you
know the pharmaceutical sector IT sector
uh critical minerals sectors and so on
and so forth right uh so if we can come
up with these arrangements with the US
that will reduce
India's exposure to these presidential
powers and uh it will shift the
relationship between India and the US
into treaty based commitments
rather than being uh being hostage to to
the whims of the president of the US. So
that is overall the situation. Um
this does give India a little more
leverage when it comes to negotiations.
Um and India should try and
you know take the relationship forward
in the right direction if possible.
Yeah, this is this does give us some
leverage.
Okay,
look at how online says Pandora Papers,
Paradise Papers, Panama Papers, Bahamas
leaks, Swiss leaks, Lux leaks, Offshore
leaks, Iraq war logs, Afghan war logs,
US diplomatic cables, Edwards Noden NSA
leaks, Julian Assange Wikileaks, Epstein
files, Ashley Madison hack and so on and
so forth. Are these naturally emerged or
uncovered exposes or eventually
published or propagated by the deep
state or any other entity in order to
drive attention of the global population
magnetically. So what online is asking
is is this natural organic genuine leaks
or the is is this or is this information
released
uh in a controlled fashion
for in order to fulfill some agenda?
That's the question.
I mean
it's it's certainly possible that uh
what you call the deep set or whatever
it may release such material from time
to time
in order
to decide to to to direct the world's
thinking to and and and
essentially to to drive narratives
that it controls. That's the question.
So I would say that some of these things
are definitely genuine leaks that have
actually hurt and harmed u the
reputation
of the US. For example, the Wikileaks
thing, Julian Assange, they really went
after Julian Assange, right? They ruined
his life.
And I would say that the reason he's
alive is because he's an Australian
citizen. If he was not Australian, if he
was from some other country, well, who
knows what would what would have
happened to him.
So, Wikileaks definitely I don't think
it was a deep state release. I don't
think they would they would have want
they I would I don't think they would
have ever released those those files
themselves, right? It's it's hurt the US
image greatly. So, that is definitely a
genuine leak. When it comes to Edward
Snowden, well, that again, I think is a
genuine leak. He genuinely uh released
and leaked this information about the
prism program and whatnot about the US
digital surveillance on on the entire
world. Much of it was focused on India
actually and Edward Snowden had to
escape from the US and he now lives in
the Russ in Russia, right? If he was not
in Russia, if Russia had not given him
asylum, he would have been somehow or
the other caught by the US and given the
harshest of punishments.
So Snowden and Julian Assange, I
believe, are organic, genuine leaks. A
lot of the other stuff
like Epstein and whatever else. Um, a
lot of that could be stage managed by
the US establishment. Epstein files
leak. Maybe they want maybe there's some
multiple reasons for it. One is to tell
the show the world that this is the kind
of people who are ruling you and you
better be careful. Don't go against us.
Right? That's one thing perhaps. The
second thing is perhaps they want to uh
discredit a lot a whole bunch of people
and push them into retirement. People
like Bill Gates and the Clintons and uh
essentially possibly even Trump
eventually once Trump is done with the
47th uh presidency. he's going to be as
relevant as Biden most likely. So,
there's multiple reasons why the Epstein
files would have been leaked. A lot of
them obviously are redacted and they're
protecting the the the accused, not the
victims.
Um, so a lot of this most likely is
stage managed. It is released
purposefully but some of it like the
Wikileaks and Edward Snood and the Prism
leak those
those were not done on purpose and that
actually hurt the interests of the US.
Aayush Singh says covery engine
afterburner tested. What's your opinion?
Gorov Pagra says, "Is making fighter jet
engines that much more difficult when
compared to nuclear reactors and
weapons? If no, then I doubt whether our
nuclear technology is indigenous. A
certain nuclear research agency use have
Russian training
for its scientists for quite some time.
Okay. First of all, Aayush Singh's
question is about cavary afterburner uh
tested cavary engine. So the cavary
engine is this indigenous engine that
India has been developing for the past I
don't know how many decades right it is
being developed at the gas turbine
research establishment in Bangaluru GTRE
and India has spent almost no money on
it I mean the Rafal deal if it happens
it's like 30 billion 35 bill I don't
know 3040 billion the total amount of
money India has invested in the covery
program over the past few decades is
like half a billion dollars so India
doesn't really,
you know,
seem to care about this. But so when it
comes to the cavary engine, the cavary
engine was supposed to be the engine
that the fighter jet will use. And uh
the theas fighter jet program actually
uses the F
104 or whatever engine. General Electric
engine, right? Which jet engine does the
the program use? One second.
Uh, Tjas jet engine.
Tjas
jet engine.
Uh, F404, right? That's the one. So, the
F404 has an output thrust of 49 kontons
dry thrust and with after burner it's
about 83 84 konton.
Okay. What's a Newton kilogram m/s
squared?
Uh, forget about that. So, the general
electric engine has a dry thrust without
after burner of 49 konton and with after
burner which is wet thrust it's about 83
84 konton. The cavary engine's dry
thrust is also 49 konton.
But for some reason the general electric
engine has been used because the cavary
engines after burner technology has not
really been developed thus far and even
when after burners were used the wet
thrust wasn't was around maybe 70 or
something kon but we want 80 plus.
So that's been the story thus far. Now
the news has emerged a couple of days
ago that the cavary engine's after
burner has been improved and tested and
it seems like this time the wet thrust
has exceeded 80 kontons
which would put the cavary engine if
this technology becomes reliable it
would put the cavary engine essentially
in a very similar league as the general
electric F104 engine
right so it's great news but I'm not
sure if it will be
Even with the afterb burner working
fine, I'm not sure if it will be used in
the pages program. So India has already
already I think signed a deal with Safon
which is a French company for the
development of an indoor French jet
engine that whose technology will be
fully owned by India. That's fantastic.
Saf already makes fantastic jet engines.
So that obviously is just going to cost
us some money and then we'll get the jet
engine eventually whenever it happens.
But in in the meanwhile I have always
said that even if we buy foreign jet
engine technology which becomes entirely
our own we should not kill the cavary
program we should continue developing
the cavary engine at its own speed at
its own pace in parallel don't kill it
off and that's what it seems like is
happening so the cavary engine is
quietly
being developed in whichever way and now
the afterburner has been tested and
looks like the after burner test was a
success and it looks like the wet thrust
is now in excess of 80 kontons or around
80 konton which is a tremendous
improvement.
So I think it's fantastic.
So it it gives us options right even if
the French thing for whatever reason
doesn't work out we will still have
this. So it's great. Um but hopefully
the saf thing works out fine. Now the
question by Gorov is is m is making jet
engines fighter or whatever he is making
jet engines way more difficult compared
to nuclear reactors and weapons. Of
course
of course a jet engine is incredibly
complicated.
A rocket engine is super simple compared
to a jet engine. Okay. A nuclear reactor
is far more well it's not that difficult
compared to the complexity and
difficulty of making a jet engine a high
quality jet engine.
A nuclear reactor is essentially you use
facile material in a controlled fashion
to generate heat. That heat boils water
and drives a steam engine. That's a
nuclear reactor in in very very simple
terms.
Okay. Of course, it's not that simple.
It's pretty complex, but not as complex
as a jet engine. Nuclear weapons, once
again, it's not that that difficult.
It's not that complicated. Rocket
engines,
ramjets, scramjets, cruise missiles,
cryogenic engines, they are not as
complex as jet engines. Okay. So, the
point is our nuclear technology is
entirely indigenous.
Entirely indigenous. No question about
that. uh Russian language training and
all. I have no idea about that. I mean
in Bhaba atomic in the BC I know for a
fact that in the 1950s and 1960s you had
to take Russian courses.
I don't know if it's still the case or
not because in the 20th century Russia
was one of the superpowers and a lot of
the physics output of the world came
from Russia and they publish in Russian.
They're not like Indian slave mentality
who publish in English, right? The
Russians published their research papers
in Russian, not in English, unlike
Indians. So if you wanted to access
Russian research, you had to learn
Russian. I'm not sure if that's still
the case, but that's a different story.
A jet engine is way, way more complex
than nuclear reactors, nuclear weapons,
cryogenic engines, ramjets, scramjets,
all of that. A jet engine is way more
complicated.
Those those turbine blades
they have to be made from a single
crystal. Each turbine blade blade has to
be a single crystal of metal of of
whatever alloy you're using. You need
advanced materials science for that. And
not just that, those
um turbine blades need to have air ducts
within them which will take hot air out
and whatever. You know, it's it's very
complicated stuff. It takes decades to
develop a worldclass
low bypass turboan jet engine. So it's
it's way more difficult compared to what
you're mentioning and please be be
certain that India's nuclear technology
is entirely indigenous.
Really now Miss Patel says a cookie in
Manipur government. Cookies given free
reign to terrorize Mate and Nagas. US
given free access to our western command
such that their admiral is is at the
center of the photos they posted. I want
to trust the government of India more
than anyone else since I have seen all
the good work they've done and are still
doing. But it looks like things are
deteriorating. Or maybe they are just
way too weak to handle the US. We'd
probably never know what gun was placed
on the government of India's head. Yeah,
nukes don't make us invasion proof. But
the opposition parties aren't even an
option for me. Feeling kind of law. Yes,
doom and gloom. Does it look like See,
one thing you be we have to be very
clear. The US is way way way more
powerful than India. There's no way if
they put a gun to your head, you can you
can you know uh not give in.
Um the US was given access to our
western command. Do we should also know
that Indian um India has also given
access to American commands like in the
same way. So it's not like uh we our
officials don't go and visit their
military command centers. We also do
that by the way. Okay. Uh but yeah, the
optics don't look very good when you
have an American admiral at the center
of the photos, right? He is the main
guy. That sort of thing. Yeah, it it's
kind of um yeah, the optics aren't
great.
Um, Manipur is a disaster. No question
about it. Manipur, it looks like India
has lost sovereignty over significant
parts of Manipur by now.
Uh, there's no other way of putting it.
Um,
and uh, all of that. Yeah. So, the
question you're really asking is is
India becoming a vasal state of the US?
Like I have said that there is a
significantly high probability of India
becoming a US Wasal in the next 5 years.
Are we on the road to that? Have we
started the process of vasalhood?
I'm not sure yet. Some indications are
not very nice, but I would say we are
still thus far mostly sovereign.
Um, you are right. We see the India is
way weaker than the US. And you, if
India does become a vasal, you can't
blame the government. The US is just too
powerful. And that's what they want.
They want India to be vasal. I think
it'll be I I I'm still optimistic that
India remains independent and sovereign
by 2030 if we are still sovereign then
essentially we'll be unstoppable but
it's um not that easy.
Uh you don't trust the government of
India more than anybody else. They've
done all the good work. They've done a
lot of good work and so on right. Um
they've done a lot of good work. They've
built a lot of infrastructure.
uh they've made India to a good extent
atma nurbar in terms of defense
equipment not entirely obviously but
that that's a long road of course
there's a lot of good work that the
government of India has done under prime
minister Modi
uh
but um there's a lot more that can still
be done right if India wants to
strengthen its sovereignty India should
deport the millions of Bangladesh living
in India
India should deport the millions of I
don't know how many Rohhingas are living
in India. I don't know how many
Pakistanis are living in India. The
cookies will not speak about them
because they have been given charge of
at least half of Manipur now. So on
these fronts the government of India is
failing
when it comes to diversifying the Indian
economy. Uh when it comes to making
India that's also not really worked out
very well thus far right. Uh India is
still heavily dependent on IT exports
which AI will eat up very soon.
India is not in the AI race despite
whatever is being claimed.
India is not in the space race anymore.
So there's a lot of things that are not
going very well. The the core issue is
reforming. I mean we need a higher
quality population
and that is entirely dependent on
dependent on the education system which
is not being reformed at all. But we
still keep on crying crying vishwa guru
vishwaguru. So it looks like there's a
lot of slogans slogan hearing and uh
more slogans than actions
right
um
yeah so there are issues no question
there are issues in India you I
understand why some people will feel low
uh I prefer to remain optimistic until
there is as long as there is any hope at
all. So I'm still optimistic that India
will prevail and in the next five years
if he has still if we are still a
sovereign nation we will be unstoppable.
We need the right leadership. We need
great leadership. We have a great prime
minister and going forward also longterm
we need great leadership. So yeah let's
let's be positive. Let us be optimistic.
Every nation has problems. Every nation
has issues and uh we are no exception.
But let's remain optimistic and work
together to in whichever way we can to
keep India going forward. Okay.
Okay.
Alex Clement says, "Big fan of yours.
Thank you so much, sir. I have recently
enrolled in a PhD program as a junior
research fellow and I'm keen to pursue
my research in geopolitics or
geostrategy. Could you kindly suggest
some relevant and contemporary topics of
research areas?"
Well, geopolitics, geostrategy, there's
so many so many topics you can you can
pick. So, for example, um India faces a
dilemma. Okay.
The dilemma is should we focus on the
maritime domain or the continental
domain. We face threats on both area in
both areas the continental domain and
the maritime domain. So for example we
have major continental threats mainly
China but also Pakistan right we even
have east Pakistan now we even have the
the whole cookie disaster in Manipur so
much so we have all these continental
threats mainly if you want to distill
down the continental threats into two
it's LAC plus LOC so that's our
continental threats we also have major
emerging vulnerabilities in the Indian
Ocean region you the Chinese
encroachment into the Indian Ocean
region and the Pakistani involvement,
the Pakistanis getting submarines and so
on so forth, right? The the the problem
of China, the problem of Pakistan. So we
have maritime vulnerabilities, we have a
continental v vulnerabilities. So
one good research topic is to study how
India allocates resources and attention
between these two major continental
threats. That's that's a great I would
say um research topic in geopolitics
geostrategy. Now since we are discussing
AI so much with the AI sub and all maybe
another topic could be AI and cyerspace
you know is AI and is cyerspace India's
uh uh what role does it play as India's
strategic force multiplier?
So you can um examine how the
convergence of these domains AI cyber
spa cyber cyber warfare and even space
capabilities in AI capabilities in
cyerspace capabilities in space how do
how do these domains and the convergence
of these domains how does that reshape
India's or how does it how is it in the
process of shaping India's grand
strategy how does it shape India's tools
of state craft how does it shape India's
deterrence how does
shape the way the India's coercive
capabilities, India's influence in the
geopolitical domain, right? Uh does
digital capability allow India to
leapfrog
its traditional power constraints? How
coherent
is India's institutional architecture
um for multi-dommain operations across
these domains and so on? That's a really
interesting topic. Then uh an evergreen
topic is India's policy policy shift
from non-alignment to multi-alignment.
Right? Now India is not non-aligned.
India is multi-aligned. Right? Uh India
is a multi- aligned nation. It India
seeks to be friends with everybody and
engage constructively in various spheres
of activities with every possible
nation. That's called multi-alignment,
not non-alignment. A lot of commentators
still say that India is non-aligned.
India is not non-aligned. India is
multi-alignment. So you could examine
India's policy shift. How did it happen?
Why did it happen from non-alignment to
multi-alignment? Is multi-alignment a
stable long-term strategy that is viable
for India? Or is it simply a trans
transitional posture that India
currently has adopted but is not going
to be viable long term? And under which
pressure points does India's
multi-alignment strategy possibly break?
Is it sanctions
imposed by
in the in the context of the Russia
Ukraine war the pressure imposed by the
US on India um does China come into the
into come as a factor into this so under
what pressure points could India's
multi-arignment possibility uh strategy
or or or posture possibly break and how
would you uh study this you could uh
study voting patterns in the United
Nations you could uh study various uh
metrics in energy in trade in defense
right you could uh look into case
studies on the Ukraine Russia Ukraine
war and its effect its first second
third order effects on India you could
look at what's happening in the
Indoacific the Middle East crisis and
what kind of effect it has on India and
so on so so India's shift from
non-alignment to multi-alignment and how
viable is this as a long-term pro
strategy and what are the pressure
points that could potentially make it
break right Um
there's so many more uh
India's domestic political economy
India's and how does it relate to
India's external strategic posture so
India has India needs growth
domestically growth imperatives for
India right India needs growth
domestically India does all this welfare
politics you know larly bhana yojana and
whatever else yojnas right uh India has
various business lobbies that are very
invested in India's growth and you know
uh that sort of thing and they impose
constraints on the kind of growth that
India can have. So how do all these
things uh
constrain or enable India's geopolitical
posture and are they conducive to bold
geopolitical moves or are they do they
constrain India from making bold
geopolitical moves um we have this
narrative of vishwaguru in India that's
very popular among politicians so and
there are people like me who who speak
about civilizational state and now
that's becoming kind of a big thing a
lot of people say that India is a
civilizational state as opposed to a
nation state, right? So, how do these
narratives of Vishaguru and
civilizational state and so on, how do
they concretely alter policy in India
and so on? So, there's there's a lot of
fertile ground when it comes to uh
topics for a PhD program. Uh my advice
for PhD for a PhD topic is don't take
something that's overly complex. Take
something that is substantial,
significant,
something that will give genuinely new
re
new material,
um,
original research possibilities
obviously,
but make sure it's not too complex.
It'll get you bogged down for like too
too long. All right, all the best, Alex
Clement.
Sam the Gamer says, "Do you see today's
deep states and intelligence alliances
like Five Eyes, US, UK, EU intel
networks, China, Russia cooperation,
etc. as a direct continuation of cold
war structures just rebranded?
If India wants to be a genuine great
power, does it also need to build its
own transnational influence network of
this kind? Or is this in incompatible
with a dharmic civilization state
approach?
So are all these inter intelligence
alliances like five eyes, UK, U, uh, US
network and so on. Are these all direct
continuations of cold war structures? We
see not necessarily. Some of these
obviously are NATO is a direct
continuation of the cold war structures.
The EU direct continuation of the cold
war structures. Five ice continuation.
UK, US, EU is kind of reconfigured but
definitely still there. Russia China is
new.
During the cold war after 1969, Russia
and China were adversaries. China was
more aligned gradually. Over time, it
became more and more aligned with the
US, at least economically,
right? But today, you have Russia and
China working together. That's
definitely not a direct continuation of
uh the first cold wars structures. It's
not a rebranded continuation of
anything.
Uh so yeah, some of these are
continuations, some of these are not.
Now if India wants to be a genuine great
power, does it also need to build its
own transnational influence network of
this kind? Of course it does. And is
this incompatible with the Dharmic
civilization state approach? Why is it
incompatible with the Dharmic
civilization state approach? Does
Dharmic approach mean that you should
not ever compete with anybody? Does the
dharmic approach means mean that you
should uh not strive to be number one?
Does the dharmic approach mean that you
should not be a global competitor?
I mean Vishnu Gupta Chanaka was a
dharmic person wasn't he? He wrote the
Art Shastra. Do read the Art Shastra in
all the measures that he speaks about.
Makya is is a child compared to
Chanakya.
Right? When it comes to for example uh
the Kushan Empire they were dharming,
right? I mean they expanded across the
whole of central Asia
they were massive the Kushan Empire was
massively expansionist
it did build its own transnational
influence network didn't it how is that
a dharmic the Morian did the same thing
the Guptas did the same thing
the chas they vasalized the whole of
Southeast Asia and they were dharmic so
nothing of the sort
nothing of this sort is incompatible
with the dharmic civilizational state
approach. I think we have forgotten what
dharma is.
We complete we have no idea what dharma.
This is the problem in India today. The
education system has dassinated
everybody. Nobody even knows what their
own own culture and religion is.
Dharma doesn't mean you you are a mute
observer of what's happening in the
world. A non-participant,
right?
It's completely compatible with the
dharmic civilizational state approach.
No question about it. We have to win.
There's nothing wrong with winning.
Okay. Mary Kane, good to see you, Mary.
American says, "Ancient original
concept, trade route, rob trade route,
secure trade route, current uh
situation, gateway, space station, earth
to moon, transfer corridor for L2, NRO,
secure communic satellite communications
and mission systems, future path to
cyber security, math and physics, B
techch and computer science or
electronics, infoch, avionics, cyber
skills, Linux, Python, TIA security,
ethical hacking, internship with US with
ISRO and or other private space tech
firms.
practice via n map metloit purple
revolution. So the question is
considering India's attention to math
and physics traditional dharmic approach
to observation without judgment cool
analytical resilience if you were in
transit between the earth and the moon
and something crazy started happening in
there maybe something goes wrong
who would you call for space cyber
security or security my first thought
would definitely be India
okay if something goes wrong okay let me
remove this so that uh my face is
visible
See, if I were in in what's once again,
if I were in orbit,
if I were in transit between the earth
and the moon, okay, let's say I'm
returning from the moon and something
goes wrong. Who would I call for
security? Who would I call to solve my
problem?
And Mary says her her first thought will
be with India.
Look, if I were in in in transit between
the moon and the earth, let's say I'm
returning from the moon in a spacecraft
back to Earth and something goes wrong,
who do I call? Who do I call? I call my
space agency.
If I am on a NASA spacecraft, I call
NASA
and tell them something's gone wrong.
Fix it. Help me fix it. You can't fix
it. I'm over here. I've got the tools.
Tell me step by step how I can fix the
problem.
first identify the problem and then then
fix it. If I am in a on on a Space X
spacecraft, I call up SpaceX
headquarters.
If I am in an ISRO spacecraft, I call up
ISRO headquarters. If I am in a
Rosscosmos spacecraft, I call Moscow or
Bikonor, wherever it is. So, who do I
call depends on which agency
has made the spacecraft I'm traveling
in. If I am on a Space X spacecraft and
I call the Chinese, they will not know
how to solve my problem. If I'm on an
ISRO spacecraft and I call up Houston,
NASA, they won't know how to solve my
problem. So, I have to call whoever has
designed and built the spacecraft I'm
traveling in. Right? That's the
straightforward answer.
uh in the past obviously India was very
very very technologically and
scientifically advanced but
unfortunately today that is not the case
not the case
um that's the unfortunate situation
India is in today it's a cyclical thing
there are cycles that that civilizations
go through you have rises you have rise
and fall rise and fall rise and fall
right now India is in in in that phase
where India has kind of fallen
India still India has a lot of rising to
do thus far and uh we are not even
getting started yet I would say
okay
RTX99
army says
to to you as well I'm a student with
history as elective subject in the
course that I've opted in and in one
instance I've stumbled upon a question
analyze the debate of various historians
regarding the Arian picnic invasion
theory, migration theory, whatever they
call it and its authenticity is
explicitly mentioned in the book in the
textbook that you're studying. Also,
this is NP 2020 national new education
policy 2020 updated edition book and it
rants pure hatred at Sanatan the Indian
civilization by stating it is of arian
influence on our society by calling
those as brahminical texts and devoid of
vic origin. Please pick this.
See, like I've said, the new education
policy 2020 is not going to solve any of
the problems that ail India's education
system.
A lot of people whoever they are are
claiming this solves all the problems
and now India is a vishwaguru education
system. That's BS.
It doesn't address any of the problems
that plague the core core issues that
plague the Indian education system.
Okay.
Does it address any of the corruption?
Does it address the issue that your
teachers the vast majority of of your
teachers and professors are are
incompetent
and worse than incompetent corrupt?
Does it address the issue of the
coaching classes mafia? Does it address
the issue that of of students having to
memorize things instead of understanding
and conceptually understanding anything?
Does it address the the the the issue
that uh in the education system of India
the
the the academic staff and non-eing
staff are the real stakeholders not the
students and their parents.
The new education policy addresses none
of the core horrible issues that plague
the Indian education system. It's a
joke. It's a cosmetic makeover. It's
like putting lipstick on a pig.
That's what it does. And here we have
another interesting
unfortunate
revelation.
Um,
so Indian civilization has Arian
influence, right? So people like me are
descendants of Arian invaders, right?
Essentially that's what it says. We
aren't indigenous. Indigenous people are
adiwasis. They are indigenous. Everybody
else is in is invaders.
And and it uses this term brahminical
text. So when you this this term
brahminism and brahminical text it was
invented invented by people like uh
I forget the name of the guy
about a century ago
RC Majunar he used the term right
brahminical text and whatnot brahminism.
So it kind of this this term kind of
implies that the brahinss rule India
and they had imposed some special
religion on India which is different
from other so it's about creating more
and more divisions within Indian culture
civilization and religion
and that's what the NP2020 textbooks
also do right
texts brahminical texts
so what can I
that there is no serious effort being
undertaken to to clean up and reform the
Indian education system. It's just pure
garbage. And as long as this continues
this country, I I don't see what future
it has.
Anyway, u thank you for letting us know
about this.
Amisha Mishra says, "I am an Indian
living in colonized India in the 17th
century." hypothetically, why do I have
less of a chance of getting shipped to
the west as a slave while my African
counterpart is more likely to be shipped
as a slave to be a slave in the western
world?
Well, one issue is geography. Let us go
to the map. Okay,
so
here's the map. Okay, we are here in
India. If you were to be hypothetically
shipped off as a slave
to the west,
then you would have to be taken from
India. And you know the Europeans did
not have the kind of slavery that the
Americans had, right?
Slaves were shipped off to the United
States mainly. A few to Europe for sure,
but not in the numbers that were shipped
off to the US. So if you were in India
and somebody wanted to ship you off as a
slave to the US, you would have to go
all the way down south, cross the Cape
of Good Hope, then cross the south
southern Atlantic Ocean, cross the
equator, and then go all the way to the
north Atlantic Ocean and reach the east
coast of the US. That's what you would
have to do if you were a slave trader
who wanted to ship Indians there. And in
those days, mortality rates were very
high and uh
um insurance was expensive and so on. So
it did not make economic sense to ship
Indians off to the US as slaves. When it
comes to West Africa, it was very easy.
You just had to cross the North
Atlantic. A much shorter and much more
direct route to the US compared to
bringing somebody from India. Right? So
it don't make any sense from to to bring
Indians as slaves and ship them to the
United States. In West Africa, you
already had these slave trading networks
that were in place in the 16 between the
15th and 17th centuries. you know the
Europeans uh they started trading with
with at various ports in West Africa and
they created this slave trading networks
where uh local Africans themselves for
monetary benefit would go and slave
would go and raid uh African communities
deeper in the interior of Africa and
bring back hundreds and thousands of
slaves and sell them to the whites who
would then ship them off across the
Atlantic and bring them to the
In the US um they would be used as
slaves on on sugar and cotton
plantations. Um you know the mortality
rates were very high um and that's why
they needed a constant you know supply
of slaves from West Africa
and that's why it made sense for this to
happen from West Africa not from India.
Um, another thing is that over time
slave, you know, slavery became
racialized. Over time, slavery became
racialized and black people became
synonymous synonymous with slaves in the
United States and across the Americas.
So, if you were black, you were
automatically a slave in the Americas.
If you were brown,
that was confusing because all the
natives in the Americas were brown,
right?
The blacks were slaves. Brown people
were like not as at the same level as
the whites. Obviously, the whites were
the superior race. Obviously, according
to them, that's the racial hierarchy
there. The racial cast system the
Europeans had constructed. So, the
Europeans, the white people were at the
top. The brown people were undesirable
and and they were a nuisance because
they existed, but they were not slaves.
And the black people were the slaves.
That was the the hierarchy of the
Europeans
in even among the whites you had various
you know divisions. We'll not go into
that right now. So um so over time
slavery became racialized and black
people were automatically regarded as
slaves and brown people not so much. Now
if you were a British occupier of India
in occupied India, British occupied
India then
initially the British were only after
plunder.
They wanted to trade eventually they
expanded in Bengal and other places and
eventually by the 19th century they
started uh by the 18th century they
started taking over a lot of India. Um
and their purpose in India was
extraction extraction extraction. uh and
also revenue, land revenue, land tax,
this tax, that tax, zaminda tax, all
those taxes, all the revenue and all the
uh resources extract that were to be
extraction, extracted out of India,
monopolization of Indian trade, all of
that. And eventually they started ruling
India, large parts of India. And they
used slavery in India. They used various
systems that essentially amounted to
slavery in India. They would force
people to build highways and roads and
bridges for no money, for no labor, for
for no for no wages. Um the riots by the
system was essentially nothing but
slavery.
Um they also sent indentured laborers to
various parts of the British Empire
which was once again another word for
slavery. Uh but when it comes to
eventually the British ruling India um
India became the target of missionaries
and the missionaries were were vultures
who were who wanted to harvest souls and
they wanted to portray their culture as
superior to Indian culture. Now Indian
culture did not have slavery. The
Islamic Turk culture had slavery but
that was not Indian culture. Right? Uh
so the British missionaries they wanted
to portray themselves as superior to to
Hindus. So they could not enslave
Indians. I mean not legally enslaved
Indians right they they had all these
systems like Zabindari Riyatwari etc
that amounted to slavery but they could
not legally do slavery in India
and uh eventually the British sought
themselves sought to port to to position
themselves as the legitimate rulers of
India and as a superior culture and
that's why once again they could not
impose slavery on India so even this
indentured system which was like
contractual system you signed a
contractor you put you put your
thumbrint and you were promised wages
eventually when you were shipped off no
one knew what happened to you so doesn't
did not matter but that's how it was so
because of these reasons if you were an
Indian person living in British occupied
India in the 17th 18th 19th centuries
you had a way less you had a much less
chance of getting shipped off as a slave
somewhere compared to somebody who was
living let's say in in the western part
of Africa
or other parts of Africa during the time
when you had Ottoman Empire and so on.
Yeah, that's why
Nirvana Shanks says the Gupta Empire is
often called the golden age of India.
What policies and science, arts and
governance contributed to this
prosperity and what could and could
modern India replicate any of these?
Thank you for your attention to this
matter. Yes. So, the Gupta period is
called by a lot of historians as the
golden age of India. It's not like it
was the only golden age but yeah it's
kind of become a cliche that the Gupta
age Gupta period was a golden age of
India. The Gupta period is in the
somewhere in the middle of the first
centur, first millennium AD, right? And
the Gupta Empire emerged out of Magad,
out of Patipotra, which is present day
Patna in Bihar and eventually the Gupta
Empire ruled the whole subcontinent and
beyond the subcontinent um parts of
Central Asia and so on. So what were the
policies that the Gupta Empire um you
know had that contributed to this
prosperity? Science and u talking about
science and uh arts and governance and
so on. What are the the policies that
that we had?
So
during the Gupta period as with other
periods in India uh the government of
India the Gupta government of India um
endowed educational and research centers
with state funding. Okay. So what kind
of educational research centers schools
temple schools monasteries universities
like Naland Takshila and so on. What
kind of endowment?
The government would give land grants.
They would give fixed monthly or yearly
revenues and they would give autonomy.
So land grant means the university gets
its own land. Certain number of villages
all the revenues of that of those let's
say 10 villages will be used for the
upkeep of the university
plus possibly you know yearly revenue
from the government plus autonomy. So
because of this you had the creation of
a class of scholars who did not have to
depend on anybody
financially. Economically the university
did not have to depend on anybody
economically. It was autonomous. It had
its own revenue plus it got more revenue
from the government. Right? So because
of this you had all these scholars who
could focus their entire entire
existence their entire life on teaching
whatever it is that they were experts in
whether it is mathematics astronomy
medicine whatever whatever whatever
right so that was fantastic that's
that's a great policy that you have um
when it comes to so there is science and
also philosophy and all the all the
academic disciplines when it comes to
arts
you know the royal court of the Guptas
was an institutionalized cultural
center.
Some of the great Gupta emperors were
Samudra Gupta, Chundra Gupta II and so
on. These great Gupta emperors
maintained a court culture in which
cultural exponents like poets, like
musicians, like dramatists and other
literary scholars etc. They received uh
stipens, they received honors, they
often received land grants, right? And
because of this this because of this
policy this this caused the
professionalization of these disciplines
of high culture. Okay. Um Chandra Gupta
he had a gathering of nine
jewels navaratna in his court. One of
the navatnas of Chandra the second was
Khaledas. Right? So this is another
example of of this policy of
concentrating talent at court and giving
it sustained support.
Right? Uh then you had uh
state resources would would go into
monument building, temple building in
India today. How many temples do you see
see being built?
Do you see any new temples being built
in India today? You see other structures
being built in India today
but not temples anymore. You hardly see
a new temple being built anywhere.
During the Gupta period, state resources
were used for monument building and
temple building. Uh the empire financed
temples, stone temp temples, uh
sculptural programs. They gave religious
endowments to uh communities to guilds
to merchant guilds to artisan lineages
long-term endowments long-term contracts
u and prestige right so this is called
this is essentially directed investment
focused invest investment and this
generated
lasting centers of uh pilgrimage of of
uh of artistic excellence of urban
activity all of
Um and this obviously supported
schools
of art, schools of iconography and so on
so forth. Stylistic experimentation
you know flowered during this period and
these schools of art like the Gandhar
and Gupta art and Matura school of art
and so on these eventually inspired the
whole of India. They became panindian
models. Right? So that is about uh arts
governance.
So during the Gupta period you had very
strong central rule but you also had a
lot of decentralization.
Yeah. Central very strong central
administration
and at the local level significantly
decentralized administration with with
local u
local prominent people local merchant
guilds taking uh you know taking the
initiative of of uh taking care of the
local ground level administration of the
empire.
So you have a strong monarchy, a strong
central system which take cares of the
geopolitics of the of the of the
military of the defense of the empire
and so on. But you have a lot of
autonomy given to provincial officials,
a lot of autonomy autonomy given to
village assemblies,
a significant amount of autonomy given
to merchant guilds. So, so these
low-level structures, ground level,
grassroot structures managed localized
justice, they managed local trade rules,
they managed the local infrastructure
with obviously financial support from
the empire from from Patutra or Matura
wherever it was eventually, right? So um
this caused a great flowering
a fluoresence
of of u trade and so much more in the
empire in in in India you know uh this
encouraged long-distance trade. It made
it easier for surplus money to be
reinvested in infrastructure in roads
irrigation um temples civic buildings so
much more. Right? So um it was a very
good system and that's the kind of
system we had for for the longest time
in India decentralization plus strong
centralization whenever you had great
empires and that's what the Gupta empire
also did and it was fantastic. So uh can
modern India replicate any of these
things in a democracy we can't replicate
any of this won't work in a democracy
you need a return to dictatorship for
this to happen imperial dictatorship.
So yeah, that's kind of uh some of the
policies. There's so many more policies
that you can speak about from the Gupta
era, but that that will take hours. So
yes, a little bit of science, arts and
governance.
Amisha says, why is South Africa the
only African country where the
population of white colonizers and their
descendants remained throughout the 20th
century and even after the 20th century?
So South Africa is kind of exceptional,
isn't it? in in in in terms of uh the
colonizers remaining after
decolonization
right when you look when you look at
nations like Mozambique when you look at
Angola when you look at Zimbabwe Kenya
etc a lot of a significant portion of
the colonizers population left after
decolonization
when it comes to South Africa I think
it's at least 5 million white people
still live there so South Africa is
definitely exceptional in this
So why is that? So first of all uh the
colonizers roots the settlers roots go
deep in South Africa. Uh South Africa
was was colonized by Europeans, Dutch
primarily eventually the English also.
So it it it all begins in the 17th
century. So it's centuries old. And
these people they set down deep roots in
the land and they develop their own
distinct identity which is no longer
purely European. It's the Africaner
identity. They have their own dialect of
of Dutch Africer and yeah so their
entire identity is distinct from the
English or Dutch identity. Right? That's
one of the causes. The roots go so deep
in South Africa.
And unlike the other countries in in
Africa that that that uh deolonized
for example Algeria, you had a war of
independence, a brutally violent war of
independence in Algeria and all white
people were essentially expelled from
Africa brutally through force
as a consequence of Algeria winning
their war of independence. when it comes
to various other African nations,
Tanzania, Uganda, Kenya and so on so
forth, Zimbabwe
um you had you know essentially u the
the colonizers being forced off right in
Zimbabwe you still have a significant
non non-negligible white population in
Botswana
uh which are the African nations let's
take a look at uh
the map.
Botswana and Namibia, you still have,
you know, white populations.
Um, Zimbabwe, you have a reasonably
uh visible,
non-trively small white population.
Kenya, you have a very few white people
now and so on. But South Africa, yeah.
So, um,
so in all these other nations, there was
a violent overthrow of colonialism more
or less. More or less. not entirely
always the same but yeah uh but in South
Africa there was a negotiated transfer
of power
okay it was a negotiated transfer of
power
um the path to majority rule in in South
Africa did not come about through
violent overthrow of the government or
revolution or a revolution it came
through negotiations
and the the colonizers voluntarily gave
handed over power to the to the to the
majority population of the country right
the ANC was unbanned Nelson Mandela was
rehabilitated and so on so forth right
um that's another contributing factor
and most importantly the economic
structure in South Africa
um it would have collapsed if the white
people left okay the white presence in
South Africa was and still is very
materially really useful to the South
African economy and it is useful to the
old elite of course the white people and
also the new elites the people who run
the South African government today and
that's why the white people still remain
there are obviously tensions and so on
from time to time you have some issues
uh Elon Musk Elon Musk keeps complaining
that there is a genocide of white people
happening in South Africa u I'm not sure
how true or false that is I haven't
looked into it so there are obviously
issues but the white population is still
central
uh in some ways to the South African
economy and they have very deep roots in
South Africa and now you have white
people marrying black people and also
eventually after a few generations it
may it may not be an issue anymore
possibly so that's why South Africa is
an exception in the among the African
countries in the case in the sense that
their white population more or less
remained intact after uh the transfer of
power
Krishna of the suryamir Netherlands
says, "Were the Yanas or the Yoners
actually Greek? And is it true that they
were related to the Cambodas? I have
heard and read that both races and
ethnicities were actually degraded or
fallen chhatrias from northwest Batwa.
What's your view and opinion about
this?"
Okay.
Um
the Greeks, the Yavanas, the Yonas. So
in Indian literature uh ancient
literature we speak about the yavanas
and the yonas right that refers to the
Ionian people Ionian people so what is
what do I mean by Ionian people let's go
to the map let us open the map and if we
go to the Mediterranean region okay
well
um this is the agency here this region
and then here
you have the sea of cit where's the
Ionian sea
um um
the Ionian se is supposed to be
somewhere here isn't it
okay uh let me just search for
Ionian Sea.
Oh, it's here. Okay. The Ionian Sea.
Okay. I was looking at the wrong in the
wrong place. It happens sometimes. This
is the Ionian Sea. It's between uh
Greece and uh Italy essentially.
And these here are the Ionian islands.
Okay. So when we speak about the yanas
we are speaking about the Ionians the
people who lived in this region
that's what we whether it is yanas or
yonas we we are referring to the Ionians
and uh this is what we the what ancient
Sanskrit texts write about they write
about the people of this region uh even
panini
is known to have spoken the yavana
language
which is the Ionian language or So
essentially he's referring to the
Greeks, western Greeks.
So the the Yanas were actually Greeks.
No question about that. Now in later
literature,
what do I mean by later literature? So
there is this event in India, right?
Alexander's attempted invasion of India
which failed uh 320 something BC, right?
After that there is the presence of
Indoactrans and Indo Greeks in the
northwestern region of India right so
those were also called yarners in later
literature post Alexander literature
and later on in the far northwest of
India the Gandhar and beyond there was
this kingdom called the Cambodas
we had 16 Mahajanapadas great republic
Republics. The Cambodas were one of the
great Mahajanapads of India. But the
Cambodas were not exactly in what we now
call India. It was Afghanistan,
Tajakistan, Turkmanistan, that region.
Uh let me let us let us take a look at
that, shall we? Once again, let me open
this. The Cambodia Mahajanapad was
essentially not in present day not
inside the subcontinent. It was kind of
outside the subcontinent.
uh Kamboa
Maha Janapada.
So Cambodia
um
that's where it is. It's beyond
Afghanistan
right Cambogia Mahajanapada.
uh if I open as always Wikipedia is not
a reliable source of information but
let's take a look at the map which is
displayed on Wikipedia on the Wikipedia
page. So if you open this you will see
that Cambodia is northwest of Gandhar
it's kind of Afghanistan Tajakistan etc
that area.
So that is the Cambodge of Mahajanapad.
If you look at today's map, the the map
of the world as it is today. Give me a
second for that.
Okay. So,
here it is. So, we're talking about this
region
um Afghanistan, Tajakistan, Usbakistan,
Turkmanistan that region that was
that was the Cambodia region.
Tajakistan,
parts of Afghanistan, parts of
Turkmanistan and Usbakistan that was
Cambodia.
So that also bordered the Indogreek
regions.
So there are texts in which the Cambodas
and the Yanas are kind of
categorized together. Categorized
together. And in the in the manuspriti
in the manusmitti the cambosjas and the
yanas and the shakas and the paratarajas
etc are
are referred to as degraded khatrias or
fallen chhatrias
which means that they are khatrias but
they don't really follow vic practices
properly. So they're kind of degraded
khatrias. They've kind of they're kind
of slightly uncultured chhatrias.
So the the the the yanas the cambogas
the shakas which is the skithians etc
were classified as degraded chhatrias.
So um and and there have been times
where the cambas and the yanas invaded
certain parts of India together as
allies.
Okay. So it's like one Mahajanapa
fighting another Mahajanapa. That's kind
of how it was. The Cambodas were their
own Mahajanapada and they once came into
Madya Bharat on an invasion.
So you have various Indian kingdoms
fighting Indian kingdoms and that's kind
of what it was like. Uh but the Cambodas
and the Yavanas were distinct. The
Cambodas were obviously either Indian or
Indic or Indo-Iranian or whatever. They
were obviously our own people. The
Persians are at that time were our
people. Today they're not but whatever.
So um the Cambodas were either Indian or
Indo-Iranian. The Yavanas were of Greek
origin.
But the Cambodas and the and the and the
Indo Greek and Indo Indobactrans were
they ruled in roughly the very similar
region northwest of India.
That's why they are often classified
together and their lifestyle may have
been similar degraded Chhatria
lifestyle. So that's why they are often
uh categorized together in various
ancient texts.
Anisha Mishra says there is a saying
that if the ancient Egyptians were as
old to the Romans as the Romans are to
us. So then who was ancient to the
ancient Egyptians? Okay. So the Romans
let's say they are 2,000 years before
us. um let's say 1 AD or let's say 30 BC
or something. That's the Roman Empire.
When was the Roman Empire at its peak?
At its peak, 1st century BC to third 2nd
century AD. Around that time, the Roman
Empire was it at its peak. So that's
roughly 2,000 years before today. So the
Roman emp,000
years older than us, let's say. Now the
beginning of of of unified Egypt is
about 3,000 BC.
So that's 3,000 years before the Romans.
So if the Romans are ancient for us,
2,000 years older than us, then unified
Egypt was 3,000 years older than Rome.
So it is more ancient to the Romans than
the Romans are to us actually. Uh but
the question you're asking is in that
case, who was ancient for the Egyptians?
To the ancient Egyptians?
So there's many u answers to that. uh
ancient Egypt let's say it's 3,000 BC
well 3000 BC is the what they call the
mature phase of the Saraswati Hindu uh
phase of Indian history right the mature
Saraswati Hindu culture which is Indian
culture obviously that's 3000 BC so that
was contemporaneous with ancient Egypt
let's say the beginnings of ancient
Egypt are 5,000 BC well the beginnings
of Saraspati Hindu of The harapan phase
of Indian history is what 8,000 BC
right it's about 8,000 BC that's 10,000
years before today
so who was ancient to the ancient
Egyptians it was us
it was us
um
there's obviously goipe
but go it's about 11,000 years old that
archaeological site but it's like two
three archaeological sites in just one
small geographical area. It's not thus
far the evidence of a proper
civilization.
Clearly, it was old and so on so forth,
but we don't know who the people were
and what their beliefs were and what
civilization were they part of if they
were part of some civilization. So, go
is old but it's not really part of some
civilization that we know of.
When it comes to the Saraswati Hindu
phase of Indian history, it's part of
our civilization and it its origins its
archaeologically attested origins go
back about 8,000 BC roughly. That's
about 10,000 years before today. So it
was ancient even to the most ancient of
Egyptians.
Sam the Gamer says, "Could India have
leveraged its massive World War II
contribution and Britain's weakened
state after the war to negotiate
independence on far better strategic
terms, for example, more favorable
borders, stronger defense guarantees,
control of key parts, or was the
partition and Messi exit essentially
unavoidable by 1945-47 given the
political realities?" See, it's like
this. 1945 Britain is destroyed by the
war.
Okay. Britain is in is in shambles. It
is in ruins
because of the war. Second world war
it's ended. In India there's no damage.
We lost a couple of million soldiers
fighting for the British. Sure. But in
1947, in 1945,446,
the Indian Navy was the most powerful
navy in Asia.
The Indian Army, the British Indian Army
was the most powerful military force,
land-based force in Asia.
The Indian Air Force was the best air
force in Asia.
We had a few British officers who
commanded a millions of Indians.
Now we talking about
negotiating independence.
Negotiating means diplomatic talks. Now
if you have learned anything from me,
you would have learned this that
diplomacy is war by other means.
Diplomacy works when you have leverage.
What leverage did India have on the
British?
The leverage was that we had
the most powerful navy, military and air
force in Asia
owned and not owned but operated by
Indian military personnel commanded by a
handful of white guys.
The leverage was that if we shot them
all,
we took everything.
That was the leverage we had. My
question is was there any need to
negotiate every anything at all?
All Mr. Gandhi had to do was to give a
direct order to the Indian military
personnel.
Shoot all your British officers and take
control.
It would have taken
less than a day for India to become
independent.
That's all it would have taken. There
was no need to negotiate anything.
Imagine the
the opportunity Mr. Gandhi had
give one every everybody would have
obeyed him, right? People worshiped him
as a Mahatma.
All he had to do was say one thing.
Shoot them all.
Shoot all your British commanding
officers. Shoot them all.
In hours, India would have been free
with the most powerful navy, military
and air force in Asia.
Why do you need to negotiate anything
when you have this?
Why
you know
how you enslave an elephant?
You you put the slave mentality in his
head, right?
So even when he's huge and massive and
can crush you just like that like an
ant, he won't do it because he has got
the slave mentality. How do circus
trainers enslave lions?
By by whipping them from the from the
time they were little cubs so that even
when they are huge and massive and
monstrously powerful, they will still
act like frightened cats.
That's the Indian slave mentality which
still exists today by the way. Which
still exists.
Why was there any was there any need to
negotiate anything?
All Mr. Gandhi had to do was to issue
the order. Issue the command. Serve your
motherland. Serve your nation. Shoot all
the white guys. Shoot the British. Shoot
them all. Take back your independence.
It would have taken a matter of hours.
Do you remember the 1946 naval mutiny?
The Navy mutinied. The British lost
control of the entire Indian Navy bar
two three ships.
And who ended the mutiny? Mr. Gandhi and
Mr. Patel.
That's why we are where we are today.
Okay.
Amisha Mishra says, "Why did Orurange
try to enforce Sharia law on Hindus but
also spent years fighting against Muslim
states in the Deakan? Was doing both at
once a strategic error? Orangzip wanted
to rule the whole of India. Whole of the
whole of the subcontinent. There were
some Muslim nisams and whatnot who were
independent
who refused to be who refused to be or
was.
So Orv wanted to crush them all.
So
he wanted to have the whole of the
subcontinent under him and then impose
Sharia on everybody across the
subcontinent. That's what he wanted.
It was not a religious matter in this in
this sense. Him fighting the Muslim
rulers was not a religious matter. It
was a geopolitical matter.
He wanted control of the whole
subcontinent. He did not want his nisams
and whoever else
whoever it was those those various small
independent states, Muslim states,
Muslim ruled states. He did not want
them to be free. He wanted their
territories also inside his empire. And
that's why he kept his spend his life
fighting them and the maratas and so on.
It's it was not a strategic error. Um
strategic his strategic error was
focusing his entire energy for decades
in the dean.
You know he made some strategic errors
but fighting the Muslims Muslim states
was not quite a strategic error.
Okay.
Sam the gamer says, "How do you assess
Shouba Subbas Chandra Bos's decision to
align with the Axis power strategically,
not morally? Was it a realistic path to
Indian independence or a geopolitical
dead end?" It was strategically correct
and morally correct. My enemy's enemy is
your is my friend. That's the that's
that's the logic. And morally, he was
fighting the enemies of the occupiers of
India. So, it's morally correct too.
Bose's decision to align with the Axis
powers was
was a gamble,
a logical gamble, kind of desperate
because see why am I saying desperate?
Because he was aligning himself with
Japan. He would have known what the
Japanese were like, what the imperial
Japanese were like, were like, what the
post maji Japanese empire was like.
Brutal. Absolutely brutal. And he would
have known absolutely he would have
known what they intended to do with
India also.
But he would have gambled that you know
if if I leverage the Japanese support
until I conquer India then I can turn
the Indian population against the
Japanese when required. That sort of
thing. So it was a gamble a desperate
gamble. There was nothing wrong with it.
It was strategically correct. It was
also morally correct. It was the most
realistic path to Indian independence
that he had.
In 47 what we got was not independence.
It was a transfer of power from one set
of crooks to another set of crooks. That
independence we got is illusory because
the structures institutions of the
British Empire have continued and they
still continue today. It's not really
independence.
You think it's independence because you
are mentally enslaved.
So Subhashundra was doing the right
thing. Didn't work out for him. But he
tried.
He put his life on the line. He paid
with his life.
True son of India.
Okay, that brings me to the end of the
questions I had selected for today. Let
us see if I have any super chats waiting
for me. Oh yes, I have 33 super chats
waiting for me. Okay, let's uh let's
take some super chat. Sure.
All right. Snik Acharia says US Supreme
Court has kicked out Trump's tariffs.
Orange man is now orange man is now
blaming Indian origin lawyers and all.
Why is he such a crybaby? What does it
tell about the deep state ecosystem?
Why is he crybaby? Um look, yeah, an
Indian origin lawyer went out went and
litigated against Trump and he won.
Uh if Trump wants to blame somebody, you
should blame the US Supreme Court. You
should blame the US laws. You don't
blame the lawyer, right? Why is he a
crybaby? Well, he that's the kind of guy
he is, right? When something goes
against him, when he doesn't get what he
wants, he throws a tantrum. That is
Trump. That's who he always has been. Uh
what does this tell about the deep state
ecosystem?
Nothing much. They're going to get what
they want anyway. One way or the other,
they're going to get what they want.
Okay.
Katos Aryan Ary Aryawasi says why Greece
Rome claimed as western European
Christian civilization if 90% culture
trade territory was in Mediterranean
Egypt West Asia Persia India
today the white man rules so he will
claim Western Europe
as
he will claim everything
he will claim claim Greece and Rome as
as as western European Christian
civilization look Rome wasn't Christian.
Rome was polytheistic. Greece wasn't
Christian. Greece was polytheistic.
They claim Alexander as their own, but
they hate polytheism. Alexander was a
polytheist. They claim Julius Caesar as
their own.
Julius Caesar was a polytheist. Augustus
was a polytheist. Marcus Orurelius was a
polytheist. All these great emperors and
these people the hero worship were
polytheists. But they hate polytheism.
Yeah, these are the inherent
contradictions in the so-called western
civilization.
Whatever they claim was great, they
destroyed it. They destroyed their own
greatness.
Of course, today they are they dominate
the world and so on that makes them
great. So I suppose from that
perspective
um but Greece and Rome were hardly
western.
I mean if western if western
civilization is um if if to be western
you have to be Christian
Judeo-Christian or whatever then Greece
and Rome are not western
neither is Egypt neither is west Asia
Persia India nothing right so inherent
contradictions in their worldview
si kachare says don't you think the
whole entire galotia university mess is
a reflection of our po poor B tech
education system most students I have
seen during Beta keys were not even
interested in the real science just some
control C controlV project. Yeah, like I
mentioned in the beginning of the live
stream this is what we what we have seen
this issue that happened which
embarrassed India
uh it is simply a symptom of the
underlying disease. The underlying
disease is the rotten education system
the corrupt education system
and
yeah it's a reflection of the education
system itself. So I I totally agree with
you. Like I explained in detail, I agree
with you.
Abai Singh says, "What is the deal with
India confiscating Iranian oil tankers?"
I'm not sure. I have heard something
about it, but I've not looked into it.
India confiscating Iranian oil tankers.
Is India doing the US's bidding?
Is India doing the what America is
telling us? That's that's a question
that is an open question. I don't have
the answer to it right now. Is it part
of an emerging pattern?
Can't say as of now. I'm going to have
to wait and watch and see and I have to
see whether more such events happen that
are part of a certain hidden pattern. As
of now, it's too early to say. It's kind
of perplexing.
Kind of perplexing. And I don't quite
know what the deal is. Until a proper
pattern emerges, I will not be able to
say exactly what what the real deal is.
So I can't say as of now. But good
observation good that you noticed it sir
by saying
what did you mean by your recent tweet a
Kaiser?
Okay since you asked I must uh show you
first of all what is why is Yeah. Okay.
Let us go to Twitter.
uh we go to Twitter. Let's open Twitter
and you will see my actual account page.
Let's go to this
and uh
yeah this is the tweet you ask me about
right uh the US Indoacific command uh
Twitter Twitter account said stronger
together US Indopaccom commander Admiral
Samuel J. Paparo visited India February
14 to 19 2026 to collaborate on US India
paired security interests and to
strengthen the nation's closed military
ties and they put out these pictures of
the guy sitting in a pages fighter plane
Indians showing him the works and uh
this sort of image where the Americans
are center stage and Indians are on the
fringes
and uh this sort of thing whatever it is
and this as Well, so that's the tweet
they put out and I said a Kaiser. A
Kaiser means hail Caesar in Latin.
Hail Caesar in Latin.
So it's simply um a commentary on the
Americans u seeing themselves as the as
the Julius Ces in the Roman Empire of
the world. It is not quite a commentary
on India becoming a vasal state yet.
It's too early to say that. But yeah,
it's a it's a commentary on the
Americans, you know, behaving like a
modern day Roman Empire.
Seizure says, "Is modernday China pure
arthastra?"
Well, they are way more chaken than
India for sure. Yeah, they are way more
pragmatic and way more practical and uh
um
more proactive in geopolitics,
geostrategically
than India historically has been. So yes
um
is it pure are their policies pure of
the shastra? No, they are also uh they
also derive a lot of their their
playbook from Sunzu the art of war which
is a book of tricks which is a book of
strategys not strategy or it's not
strategy it's strategims uh but yeah um
their their policy is uh legalistic and
sunzuic sunzuish more than
yes they they play the game of
geostrategy
much more proactively and and much
better than India India historically has
done.
Sandy says with US Supreme Court
striking tariffs should India rework the
trade deal.
Uh look the trade deal hasn't been
signed between India and the US. It has
not been signed yet. What has been
announced is a a framework for an
interim trade deal or a framework
arrangement for an inter interim trade
deal.
So a trade deal has not been signed. We
can certainly now kind of rework it for
sure. We we now have some more leverage
like I explained in detail some time
ago. We have more leverage. The US are
the Trump administration will now
operate will now operate under more
constraints, more legal constraints that
in that it than it previously did. So it
is certainly advantageous to us and we
can try and rework and renegotiate uh
some of the parameters of this uh trade
agreement. Right? It's it's not become
an agreement yet. We haven't signed it
yet but uh we should certainly um push
for
um sector specific arrangements if
possible. We want our objective should
be to reduce our reliance on the whims
and fancies of the American president
the emergency style presidential powers
of Trump right we should try and shift
the relationship the India US
relationship into treaty based
commitments and maybe sector based
commitments that what that's what we
should do and this uh Supreme Court
judgment in the US has certainly give us
uh given us more negotiating leverage
Okay. Sam the gamer says of
Afghanistan and Israel how somehow
sovereign. Please compare the two.
Afghanistan Afghanistan's economy is
next to nothing. When your economy is so
small, you have tremendous constraints
that
essentially make you non-s sovereign.
You are tremendously dependent on other
countries. Then if you're dependent on
other countries like the like the
Taliban is dependent on the US, the US
pays the Taliban a weekly stipend of
anything between 50 to 100 million in
cash when that is what runs the Afghan
economy and government. How can the
Afghanistan how can Afghanistan be
sovereign even if you're not taking a
stipen from some other country? Let's
say you are Mongolia small country with
a small hu big country with a tiny
population and tiny economy. You are
dependent on on so many other countries
for everything.
When you are dependent on others,
you don't have full sovereignty. So
Afghanistan, there's no question of
sovereignty. Israel, come on. Israel is
super sovereign.
Israel is super sovereign.
Uh Kakashi says, "Imagine if India chose
to become a massive Hindu communist
industrial state on the scale of USSR or
China, not a US Anglo Vasal with cast
divisions.
Hindu communism, that's really
interesting. Hindu communism,
communism means collectivism.
Can that work within Hinduism?
with cast divisions. So we did not have
cast divisions. We had the vernati
divisions which were not divisions which
were occupations.
Obviously a goldsmith and a missile
manufacturer will not be the same
occupation right and let's say your
whole family is invested in this thing
and it's it's a family occupation you're
going to have different totally
different lifestyles and everything. So
that's what we had. There was a jati
verna jati system and of course there
were the four rough subdivisions of
society which are the oral verers there
was mobility among the among the verers
and so on um
Hindu communism means collectivism it
doesn't work that way if you have cast
divisions divisions you can't
collectivize things
um
but imagine if India be chooses to
become to revert to its civilizational
roots and all that would be fant
Fantastic.
Cole Ken Kane says, "What's a P and
junction diode?" H that's a blast from
the past. A P and junction diode. That's
a semiconductor thing, right? PN
junction diode. Uh this
electronics, a subject I loathed. It's
it's very interesting for a lot of
people, not for me. I don't It's a
transistor.
Yeah. depending on the current it
I I' I'd rather say you look it up man I
don't remember right now P and junction
diodes
transistors
yeah first year second year of BSE or
whatever
nothing that ever interested me so I I
don't remember right now sorry maybe I
should kind of remember it because it's
basic physics not really basic physics
but but yeah I am I'm into pure
theoretical physics. This sort of thing
was always anthemma to me.
It's a switching junction of some kind.
You apply current and the whole thing
becomes uh starts conducting the Yeah,
look it up please.
Applied electronics. Yikes. Gora TV
says, "Do you possess Do you think the
US possesses some kind of alien
technology? only the US is able to
develop tech like the SR71 Blackbird,
F117, um the stealth bomber, B2, super
carriers, etc. While no country, not
even Russia or China are even close.
Well, first of all, the Chinese are
building super carriers now. The Chinese
are building super carriers. Uh when it
comes to to the stealth technology,
well, I'll tell you what, the Horton
brothers did it before the Americans.
What am I talking about? I'll tell you
what, the Horton brothers. Okay. Horton
brothers.
Ah,
so
Walter Horton and Rhymer Horton were
were German brothers, okay?
And they came up with this design.
They came up with the flying wing
design.
The Americans obviously acquired German
technology after 1945 and they it's
DARPA and the Americans who eventually
developed it into the um flying wing
technology that we have that these US
stealth bombers have today. Right? And
the Russians also have the
okay. The Russians also have that. See
oknik
uh S20 S70. Right? Here we have it. The
Russians also have it. Even the Chinese
have various flying wing designs now.
It's not some alien technology. Okay. So
the flying wing design is a German Nazi
design from the 1930s and 40s that the
US then took forward and with advancing
technology they were able to make it
work.
Then the Russians also have it. The
Chinese also have it. India also has
this DRDO
um gatak thing. Right. Yeah. When it
comes to super carriers, the Chinese are
building super carriers. They have plans
to build super carriers that are bigger
than the US super carriers. Uh SR71
Blackbird Blackbird incredibly fantastic
aircraft.
Uh but 1970s technology it's retired now
because because of various reasons. Uh
so you know that's about the specific
examples you've given. So the question
is do I think the US possesses some kind
of alien technology? I don't I am very
very skeptical about this. The US has
the best
research ecosystem in the world.
They put their money in the right
places. DRDO in India of India was
founded in 1958. DARPA of the US was
also founded in 1958. DARPA has given
the US incredible groundbreaking
technology.
DRDO, what has it done? Why is why is it
so? DARPA has 150 employees on its
payroll. Not a single manager only 150
employees their budget is whatever it is
like twice of DRDO a few billion dollars
but DRDO is is not like 10 times less
funded than DARPA it's only half as
funded as DARPA which is tremendous it
does a tremendous amount of money but
DRDO has 30,000 employees out of which
25,000 are non-scientific employees
that's why DRDO gets nothing done
nothing of any significance nothing
groundbreaking
so the US has a right system. They have
the money and they put their money in
the right place. I doubt if they have
any alien technology. They are simply
20, 30, 40 years ahead of everybody else
because they choose to be that way and
they put their money where the right in
the right places. That's why they are
ahead of everyone.
Gora TV says, "Do you think that with
silver's increasing demand for its use
in advanced technologies, it could
eventually re reach price parity with
gold?" I doubt that.
Silver and gold is just way more
rare than silver. Silver I mean how much
silver is on the planet? How much gold
is on the planet? Okay, let's see um
how much silver and gold is there in the
world? Let's see estimated approximately
212,000 metric tons of gold have been
mined throughout history. Um for silver
1.74 million metric tons have been
mined. Okay.
So
way more silver than gold. Way more
silver than gold. So I don't expect
silver to ever reach price parity with
gold. It it's very unlikely in my
opinion.
Ken Kane says, "What do you mean by a
power factor
and the concept of phase difference
current and voltage? Why do you mean by
voltage phasers like voltage having
angles? I don't remember any of these
concepts now.
I'm very sorry. This is applied
electronic uh applied electromagnetics.
Uh this it's been too long since I
studied this stuff. This was probably
during my BSC and I have never used it
after I got out of my BSC. I've never
used this stuff.
Phase difference five. I remember that
stuff. Yeah, I mean I vaguely remember
it. Phase difference current and voltage
V voltage phases power factor. I I don't
remember these concepts anymore. It is
it I've never used it after I left BSC.
I went straight into quantum mechanics
and other stuff. So this stuff I don't
remember. I'm very sorry.
You make me feel like I'm giving a Yi
and I've not studied at all. But no,
it's been too long and this has not been
ever relevant to my work. So sorry.
Gear TV says, "Is there any way India
could render Pakistan's nuclear
infrastructure ineffective? Why cyber
warfare? And could Pakistan potentially
do the same to India?
Why cyber warfare? Well, if Pakistan's
nuclear infrastructure is if the command
and control
uh if if it's controlled
um through the internet in some way or
if it is controlled electronically in
some ways and there is no air if there
is the lack of air gapping or whatever
it you could possibly do it
uh cyber warfare wise. Otherwise, uh if
their if their warheads are not mated to
missiles and if we know where the
warheads are stored, we could take out
those locations through massive
uh missile strikes. Yeah.
So, the key is to know exactly where the
warheads are stored.
And if you have very fastmoving missiles
like the Brahmos, then you could take
those locations out in a matter of
minutes after the launch. So for a
brahmos missile to to hit a location in
Pakistan let's say karatunwa would take
maybe 5 minutes after it's launched
that's not enough time to take out the
warheads from wherever they are stored
and all.
So if this can work only if India knows
exactly the pinpoint locations of where
the warheads are stored and in case they
are already mated to launch systems then
it is then it becomes much more
difficult. So overall it's very very
difficult and similarly for Pakistan
they would have to know exactly where
India's warheads are stored which is
almost impossible because India is so
large
right India India is a gigantic nation
compared to Pakistan how will the
Pakistanis know where we have stored or
where they are storing various warheads
so it's easier for Pakistan it's easier
for India compared to Pakistan it's
almost impossible for Pakistan to do
that do to do this
current electronics I don't electronics
was a subject I did not ever like. Okay.
Um
so I I don't remember this stuff.
Electronics I I loathed the electronics.
Every moment I had to study electronics
was one moment taken away from quantum
mechanics or something more interesting.
So I don't know. I'm very sorry Ken
Kane. Electronics is not my cup of tea
at all. It I I for me it was a waste of
my life. It was a waste of my time.
Electronics not the thing for me. Sorry
sir.
Gura TV says, "Could you please suggest
a few skills or qualities that one
should aim to acquire in their
lifetime?" It depends on what you want
to be and what you want to achieve in
life.
One skill that will always be useful to
you is reading because reading rewires
your brain in a way that other people
don't that that other brains don't have.
You see, reading takes patience.
And reading also increases your
vocabulary.
Reading broadens your horizons. Heading
reading uh sharpens your focus. It
builds patience.
It gives you a longer attention span.
One central skill I mean is reading.
The people who run the world, who rule
the world, the most successful people in
the world are all readers. They read.
today's generations, youngsters today in
the teens and all, they can't read a
book. They don't have the patience to
read one page.
That's that's a big problem today. So,
one skill is reading. Other skills and
qualities and all, well, it depends. It
depends on what you want to be, what you
want to achieve and so on.
But one thing I will say is please
if you want to
stand out, if you want to be abnormal,
not be normal, be abnormal, be
different.
If you want to be different in today's
world, reading is a superpower. Reading
will will
it it gives you superpowers.
So that's one thing I would say. Other
skills and qualities, I don't know. Uh
other skills and qualities
Critical thinking obviously is is a
great skill to have.
Um what else?
Other skills and qualities be strong, be
fit, eat well, all that stuff. Eat
clean, do pranayam
and so on.
Deep learner says playing catch-up with
AI is chasing a fastmoving target. India
should instead as a civilizational force
try to infiltrate a deep tech industry
as much as possible and try to colonize
them from inside. Well, sure I am not
opposed to that but uh it's not that
easy, right? Um the US
treats is its its tech se tech sector
uh
as as as you know
the US treats its technology as uh
as as vital.
Um
the point is it it uh treats its
technology as as state secrets
and there are lots of these companies
for example take the example of Space X.
You can't be an employee of Space X if
you are on a green if you're on on a H1B
visa or something.
I don't know if we even if you have a
green card I don't know if you can be a
SpaceX employee. Let's see. Uh, can a
green card holder
become a Space X
employee?
Space X employee.
Uh, yes, a green card holder can become
a SpaceX employee. Can a H1B visa
holder?
H1B visa holder.
Yeah, very difficult. So there are
certain sectors where the Americans
won't even allow foreign citizens to
work, right?
Um the Chinese have tried all kinds of
things to to and they have been
successful in a lot of ways in
extracting uh vital technologies out of
the US. So my point is everything is
fair in in in in geopolitics.
Uh but for this to happen, India needs
the right leadership. India needs to
have a clear long-term goal set of goals
and mission. I'm not sure if that is the
case. I hope I'm wrong. I I hope I hope
I'm completely wrong. But what you're
saying is is I agree with you, but it's
very easy to say this, very hard to do
it, but I agree with you. I agree with
you.
Colin Kane says, "I am an electrical
engineer." I could say I could sense
that you're an electrical engineer.
You're currently in research and design
power electronics products. Designing a
PFC rectifier. Look it up. Vienna
continued. Since it has a very complex
system, its control algorithm is pretty
complex. Continued.
Yet Chat JPD generated a working control
strategy and code in seconds. Very
accurate.
Yeah. Well, Chad GPD is if you if you
know how to use AI today, AI will will
solve so many of your problems. Chat GPD
and various other AI systems are very
advanced today. Uh you know what they
talk about? They talk about onehotting
one code. You can just vibe code stuff
today. Apparently, you just tell tell
the AI what kind of website you want and
in in a matter of like 3 4 minutes, it
will create a whole website for you. And
when it comes to these uh engineering
problems, electrical engineering
problems and so on, it can give you
solutions
strategies like essentially on demand.
Incredibly accurate, incredibly powerful
uh
these LLMs are. So imagine how power the
kind of power that technology gives in
your hands. Now, the US and China have
AI systems that are like thousand times
more powerful than what you what you see
behind closed doors. The US military has
access to military AIs that are way more
powerful than the most powerful and
expensive AI system available to the
public. Uh what's the most expensive
Chad GPD subscription? Like $200 a month
or something. Yeah, that is the most
powerful Chad GPD version, right? That
will be nothing compared to the power of
the US military's AI. Nothing.
So imagine the power that the US has in
its hands today. And even the Chinese
have such products products and that's
how far behind India is in this matter.
But yes, I what you are saying is
absolutely accurate.
Died with Priusian says is Ukraine
finished forever? Future of Russia and
EU. Uh Ukraine's demography is is
destroyed. Most of their young men are
dead. Uh is it finished forever? It
depends. It depends on the outcome of
the war. If the war ends soon, then the
process of rebuilding Ukraine can begin.
Ukraine should be rebuilt. And look, the
Ukrainian people are Slavic people just
like the Russians. They are almost the
same people as the Russians, right?
So I suppose Ukraine and Russia can be
reintegrated sometime in the future and
then the demography will be fine.
Um future of Russia and the EU we'll see
about that. EU doesn't seem to be in
good shape now. Uh Europe is going to
slowly decline uh economically
the next couple of decades that is that
much is quite clear now as long as it is
dominated by by NATO. Russia it once
again depends on the outcome of the
Russia Ukraine war and it also depends
on the uh on the transfer of power
whenever it happens from Putin to
whoever comes next. So lots of factors
that are in play and
and can affect the outcomes. So can't
say as of now
u okay current has said normally takes
days to design and simulate in in mat
lab. Okay, Mat Lab.
Yeah, the the work that you do takes
normally takes days to design and
simulate in MATLAB. But Chat JPT can
give you the answer like that. Like that
like in a matter of minutes, right? If
you give it the right prompt, if you
give it the right context and exactly
what you seek to do, Chhat JPT can solve
the problem for you. Incredibly powerful
system indeed.
D with Priosian says, "Your opinion on
the talk of additional S400 orders by
India?" I think it's a good good idea.
Um the S400 system is one of the most
powerful uh air defense systems in the
world, integrated air defense system and
it's performed really well in operation
and u it can also be very useful when it
comes to the defense of our northern and
far eastern territories. So it makes
sense to have more S400s. Uh if we are
ordering more, it means that we have
been very impressed with it. Otherwise
we would not order more. So I think it
makes sense. It makes sense to have
more.
Abishek Singh says how how did how
castbased regiments formed must be
abolished. The British formed these
ethnic and castbased regiments and then
after 1947 the slaveminded Indian
rulers continued that Rajput regiment,
Marata regiment, Sikhar regiment, etc.
regiment, that regiment, um Gorha
regiment. So there the so the British
did a great job of dividing India. um
they classified certain
groups of people as what marshall races
and they classified certain groups of
people as as as criminal tribes or
something. They did a great job of
dividing India and they named various
regiments after um these this cast right
now we have Naga regiment we have
continued the same policy. So if you can
have a Naga regiment, why can't you have
an Arunatal regiment? Why can't you have
a Manipur regiment? Everybody will then
ask these questions. If you can have a
let's say a Sikh regiment or Garwal
rifles, why do you have to name
regiments based on on on casts or ethnic
groups or or or regions?
The Romans never made this mistake. They
gave their their legions numbers.
So I think it's not a good idea. Just
because it's a tradition that has come
from British times doesn't doesn't mean
it's a good tradition.
I would say this should be abolished.
But will the government of India abolish
this? I don't know. I don't think it's a
good idea at all to have this.
Abai Singh says do you why do you think
we'd be unstoppable after 5 years?
Wouldn't they just vaselize us 5 years
later? What can change in 5 years? In
five years, India can become a very
powerful nation.
In five years, if we really really get
our act together, we can double our GDP.
In 5 years, we can become a very
dangerous military.
In 5 years, we can acquire, let's say,
200 more fighter planes, maybe u 20 30
more ships.
and uh we can develop technology for
technologies for um better missile
systems. Maybe in 5 years we can create
a stockpile of let's say 50,000
missiles.
So we can do a lot in 5 years.
Once you reach a certain stage of your
economy and military power, it's very
hard for the others to vaselize us. In 5
years we can potentially become the most
powerful force in the Indian
subcontinent more powerful than the US
presence in the subcontinent. It's
possible.
So 5 years is a rough estimation. It
could even be 10 years but it's possible
in 5 years. And that's why I say
it'll be hard to varize us after 5
years.
If we remain independent and sovereign
for five years then we'll become
possibly unstoppable.
Yep.
Okay. E Republic of India says reduced
oil imports from Russia. Stepped back
from Chabahar Chabahar port reliance
received approval for Venezuelan oil
joined US-led pack silica. Seized three
Iran linked coast tankers. Are we now a
US vasal? I am keeping score sir. I am I
am keeping spo score. I am keeping track
of all these developments. I am also
looking into the AI developments. Tax
silica is very interesting. Um and you
have done a very good job of listing out
these concerning matters.
One thing I can tell you is that we have
not stopped oil imports from Russia. We
seem to be still
importing oil from Russia. We haven't
stopped it entirely which is a good
thing. So that is the absence of one red
flag. If we had completely stopped oil
imports from Russia that would have been
a very big red flag. Chabaha happened
before but it's also recent
Venezuelan oil. Okay fine.
That in itself doesn't make you a Wasal
join USled Pilica. We will have to see
what are the terms and conditions of
Pilica.
seized three Iran link host tankers
maybe we is doing uncle Sam a favor so
these all these different data points
all these different actions they kind of
seem to lead in one direction
but that doesn't necessarily make us a
vasal just yet just now as of now see
when Chadati Maharaj was starting off he
also had to make certain compromises
right
so right now we are not powerful. So
sometimes you have to make these
compromises. Uh but certain red lines
must not be crossed. So I would say we
are not yet a US fasile. Not yet.
But these developments when seen
together like you very well pointed out
are concerning but we are not yet a US
vasar still too early. Vladimir Ayar
says,
"Is it weird that I feel like Buddha's
Shunata and Adi Shankarachari's
non-duality are just different sides of
the same coin? Also, the renounced
debate was not actually the fall of
Buddhism in India.
I am not very cons convergent with
deeply with these concepts whether it is
adwit nonduality
or shunata I have not I have not studied
these in depth so I don't think I'm the
right person to comment about this but
like I've said most Buddhist concepts
are just
they're just older concepts repackaged
right
Um what do you call Hinduism and
Buddhism are essentially the same thing.
Uh like Alan Watts said, Buddhism is
simply Hinduism stripped down for
export. Uh Alan Watts
uh Alan Watts was a British American
writer philosopher blah blah blah. So uh
Buddhism is Hinduism stripped
down down
export.
uh his assertion that Hindu that
Buddhism is Hinduism stripped for export
refers to the idea that the fact that
Buddhism distilled the essential
universal spiritual philosophies of what
we call Hinduism while discarding
various complex localized rituals and so
on. So Buddhism is nothing but
repackaged Hinduism
stripped down for export so that
non-Indians could understand it better.
That's it. That's what it is.
Dark Side of the Moon says, "Study
guide. Why weak Pakistan shows zero fear
of India's navy and missile sustains
terror 2611 humiliates seven jets?
Humiliates seven jets." Well, that's
interesting. Is it bed bad tech terrain?
Why no real deterrence? So, this claim
of seven jets humiliated, that's that's
uh in my opinion BS. Okay. Uh why does
Pakistan operate with impunity and not
show fear or whatever?
First of all, they have nothing to lose.
They are a ruined nation.
Sadly,
and they have plenty of cannon fodder
people.
The Pakist the people who rule Pakistan,
they don't care about their people in
their nation. They don't care if India
guns down 50 terrorists who are trying
to infiltrate or cross over the border.
They don't care. Those people are car
for them.
If India, if there's a war between India
and Pakistan and India, let's say uh and
let's say 10,000 Pakistani troops are
killed fighting India, the Pakistani
generals don't care.
And lastly, they have the support of the
superpower, the US, against India. They
know the US will come and intervene
before Pakistan is destroyed because
Pakistan is important to the US
and Pakistan. So because of these
reasons Pakistan behaves the way it
does. I don't agree with this claim that
Pakistan shot down 27 or whatever Indian
jets. That's that's BS. But uh yeah and
also because India historically has
behaved like a punching bag that has
also emboldened Pakistan. Now it's not
the case but historically India has
behaved like that. So because of these
reasons Pakistan has historically
behaved the way it does and still tries
to behave that way.
Amul Desh Pande says, "Does the US
amplify or suppress certain social media
voices to shape narratives? How can
Indians tell if influencers are
genuinely independent or backed by
political or financial interests? Does
the US amplify or suppress certain
social media voices to shape
narratives?" Yes, it does. They will.
Why not?
The social media platforms are American
platforms. The US will do whatever it
wants. Should we blame them? I would do
the same thing if I owned a social media
platform. I would I would suppress all
anti-India voices. I would do that. I
don't believe in democracy on social
media.
So the US does that. I don't blame them
for doing that. Uh how can Indians tell
if influencers are genuinely independent
or backed by whatever interests? When
you have an influencer who comes out of
nowhere and becomes suddenly super
popular with 10, 15, 20 million
followers overnight essentially
that's not organic that's artificial
and especially if they give platforms to
deep state voices or whatever and I'm
just saying not necessarily deep state I
will not discuss Indian politics local
politics but the same principles apply
even in local politics.
So yeah, I mean if you are sensible, you
can tell what is artificial, what's not.
Uh Rush God says, "What's this new DNA
study saying of Indians?" I have no
idea. I haven't seen any new DNA studies
of late of Indians. So I can't say, sir.
Sorry. If you can tell me the name of
the study and who did it, I could
perhaps look into it, but I have not
seen any new study recently. So sorry,
can't say. Katos says if rigid date 1500
BC is blender then WB opishad 600 BC
Buddha 500 BC Chanaka Moria Ashok 300 BC
puranas whatever date Adeshanka whatever
AD I think all these dates need to be
revisited to be very honest
um it's very possible that the date of
the Buddha and the Mahavira in Mahavir
could be maybe a0 thousand years before
what we believe it is. It's it's quite
possible. We also had multiple rulers
named Chandra Gupta. How do we know
which is which?
The ruler we call Ashoke. Most of his
inscriptions say Dwanama Priya Priya.
How do we know it is actually Ashoke?
Adish Shankarachara. Once again we I
don't know about the date.
I think a lot of this Indian chronology
has to be revisited.
And a lot could potentially changed. The
date of the rigida it's being 1500 BC is
an absolute laughable joke. It's
reasonable.
Yeah. So
Ani Sharma keeps reminding about Tumb. I
haven't seen it yet. I haven't seen it.
Sorry. I'll see when I can. I can't
promise exactly that this week I'll see
it or whatever, but I I've put it on my
to-do list to watch list. So I shall see
it when I can. And thank you for keeping
me keeping on reminding me sir. Anish
Sharma. Thank you sir.
Amisha says sir you are best Jam Ju
Krishna. Thank you ma'am. Thank you so
much. I really really appreciate you
asking all these very interesting
questions. I I sometimes wish I should I
should do one episode only for the
questions you ask but then everybody
will be very upset with me. That's why I
take like four or five questions from
you every time. But thank you so much
ma'am and thank you so much for your
very kind words. Jes Ram and Jesh
Krishna to you as well.
Pratep Kumar Roy says about 1933 Moolok
ceremony. I have no idea what that is.
1933 Moolok ceremony. Um 1933
ceremony. What is that
dramatic scene in the Romance of a
People?
Soldierfield Chicago etc. MO.
Uh do we have images of that?
Okay, I'm not aware of this stuff. Looks
like something happened in Chicago in
1933. Why did it happen and so on? I
I'll need to read about that. But
interesting.
Pratip Kumaro is about Professor Jang's
channel, Predictive History. I haven't
seen that yet. I haven't seen Tumbad
yet. I haven't seen this channel yet.
But thank you for the reminders. I will
look it up.
Thank you.
Angad Graval says, "Why do our Indian
people cater to white people when they
come to India? they complain here and
mistreat the our people in their
country. Um multiple factors. First of
all, Indians believe that we should
treat all guests with tremendous respect
and love and courtesy and all that. And
when people come from other countries to
India, they are all our guests, right?
Uh
that sort of thing. Treat all guests as
if they are God themselves, as if
they're called God himself, right? That
sort of thing or herself, whatever. So
we treat our guests as if they are go
the Sakshhat incarnation of God.
And secondly, Indians have the slave
mentality,
inferiority, complex slave mentality.
All that that also contributes to the
way Indians are so obscious and slave
slavish in their behavior when it comes
to foreigners. You will see that uh in
uh hotels, in restaurants, the the the
waiters will will treat foreign guests
with extreme courtesy and lot of
attention and they will not pay the sim
same amount of attention to Indian
guests in restaurants. That's one
example. In hotels, if you are a
white-skinned person, you will get a
special attention from the concierge and
all that. If you are not white, if
you're just Indian, you will be treated
courteously but not with that same level
of attention. So it's it's slave
mentality also. So it's a combination of
multiple factors.
Litar says
why does Iran continue uranium
enrichment despite heavy sanctions?
Giving it up could boost economy, oil,
trade and reduce unrest. Why is it so
reluctant? Because Iran desires to be a
sovereign nation.
That's why give everything up become a
slave then you will have better economy
trade all that agree to all the American
demands
you will have lifting of sanctions
why does Iran resist this because Iran
wants to remain sovereign as sovereign
as possible
that's the reason why Iran has
self-respect
that's why Iran does this and if if Iran
can continue uranium enrichment Then
they can build up their stocks of file
material
which can not only be used in nuclear
reactors for power generation. They can
also be used if the file material is
highly enriched. It can also be used in
nuclear weapons. If you have nuclear
weapons then other nations will be very
very worried about poking you. That's
why Iran does that. You see
Pratip Kumar Roy says about the film The
House of Roshild 1934 and the Rochils
1940.
Also check out Assassin's Creed logo.
Okay, I haven't seen these movies. Let
me check out the Assassin's Creed logo.
Yeah. Uh Assassin's Creed
logo. What is that? Okay. Is that
something
to do with the Freemasons or something?
Looks like that perhaps. Uh okay.
Interesting.
There are hidden there is hidden hidden
symbolism everywhere, isn't there? Looks
like that. It's possible.
Priam says, "More power to you, sir.
Thank you so much, sir. Thank you so
much."
Um Sam the Gamer says, "I meant
Afghanistan can't be armed twisted on
Dan border."
Well, every nation has some red lines
and the Afghans, the Taliban has some
kind of deal with the US, right? The the
DHA accord. There will be clear terms
and conditions in that and one of the
terms I expect will be that the US will
not, you know, bother will not interfere
in Afghanistan's territorial dispute
with Pakistan. That could be the case.
Pratep Kumar Roy says, "Are there any
Hindu religious institutions in India
free from Freemasons or the West?" I
don't know about Freemasons in the west.
So I can't say about Freemasons. RSS,
ISha, RKM, Iscon, etc. Everyone seems to
have links to Freemasons. Okay. I don't
know anything about this. I haven't
studied the Freemasons. I don't know who
they are. I don't know what their agenda
is. I know they exist. I know some
famous Indians are said to have been
Freemasons. I know that the Freemasons
have a definite presence in India. They
have the Grand Lodges or whatever in
India. But u beyond that, I don't know
much.
I don't know if all these organizations
that you're talking about are have links
with the Freemasons. I'm not sure about
that.
So I don't have the answer to your
question sir. Sorry.
Vihanka says how are you? I'm good sir.
How are you doing? Uh the question is
why is it in the 20th century where
skills should matter the most? We are
still stuck on degree based and college
based hiring and salaries in most of
industry.
Well, it's changing in the US.
For example, Elon Musk doesn't care
about your degree. If you are, you know,
applying to Tesla or SpaceX, no one asks
you about your degrees. They only see
what skills you have. And that's
increasing the case, increasingly the
case in the US. Many of these new
startups and companies and even older
companies don't no longer care about
your degree. They want to see what
you're capable of doing, what skills you
have, what portfolio you've built up for
yourself. So, that's the case in the US.
US is
the world's leader in technology and
it's the greatest nation in the world,
the most powerful nation in the world.
No question about it. India is this
third rate backward country today. The
system is third rate and backward. Why
is India third world country? Because of
its third rate backward system
where entrenched interests
ensure that change change doesn't
happen, reform doesn't happen. So for
example, if you have degree based
hiring, which means students students
need to study and pass exams and get
degrees, then that sustains this entire
coaching class mafia.
The coaching class, the people who run
coaching classes are very very rich,
very wealthy.
They are invested in the system. If the
system is reformed, it will destroy
their their their their business,
their their means of creating wealth. So
they won't allow it to be destroyed.
So these parasites who suck, who leech
off the lifeblood of the country, they
will prevent they will do their best to
prevent the system from from being
reformed. And that's why India is still
stuck in these archaic
modes of education, this archaic system.
Right? That's one example of of what's
wrong with the Indian education system.
Lar says your take on the release of the
UFO alien files. Well, it's not been
released first of all. Yeah, it's not
been released yet. Trump has said that
he will release some documents. Well,
we'll see what it is like when it's
released. Um,
it's possible the release could be
similar to the Epstein files release
where a lot of the key information is
blacked out. It's redacted. That's a
possibility. Uh, the second possibility
is maybe this will be done to to draw
the world's attention away from where
the world really should be paying
attention. Maybe a US invasion of some
nation or something. That's possible.
The third possibility is that maybe
these UFO files will have these
documents, American government documents
that claim that we have been visited by
aliens and we have communication and
all, but it's just a claim printed on
paper. They will not release any actual
evidence of alien life or whatever. So
my position, my take is that I am super
super skeptical about this matter. Let's
wait and watch what's released. I am
pretty sure no actual evidence of alien
life will be released. I'm pretty sure.
I hope I'm wrong. I'll be thrilled if
I'm wrong, but I suspect I'm going to be
right. We'll see.
Many Kazarees
says with the shift towards agentic AI
and coding agents, what's your take on
the future? How do you see India
evolving in this new agentic era? Well,
these AI agents, you know, agentic AI,
it's like a it's like a digital
employee. So agentic AI is AI that can
do things on its own. You you give it
the context. You tell it what you want
to achieve. You give it access to
whatever files, folders you have,
and you train train it over time. It's
like training uh a fresher, right? A
person who's just come out of college
and is is starting as as first time, you
know, employee of yours. So you got to
spend some time training that person.
Maybe a couple of weeks you train the
person, right? At least a couple of
weeks. Typically it's like a few months
you train the person over time you make
them better. So you train these agentic
AI systems, these AI agents and they
will learn very fast if you know how to
prompt them, if you know how to what
what kind of context to give them and
they're going to replace
entry- level employees,
right? This is going to decimate the
Indian IT sector and AI is getting more
and more powerful each iteration
and the time frames are getting more and
more compressed. the uh time between
chart GBT 4.5 and whatever the current
iteration is you know 3 what's the
current chart GBT version whatever it is
let's let's say it's 4.2 then the time
it took between 3.0 and 3.1 may have
been 6 months but the time it took
between 4.1 and 4.2 to maybe like 6
weeks only right so the time frames are
getting compressed and the AIS are
getting more and more powerful this is
going to decimate the Indian IT industry
yeah and the Indian IT industry is one
of the major sources of Indian India's
foreign exchange foreign revenue
so how do I see India evolving in this
new agentic era where it's going to be
very very tough for the Indian IT
industry it's going to be great for
Indian startups who will leverage
American AI systems Chinese AI systems
and whatnot
Um what this this new thing I've heard
about uh moldbot open close or something
which seems to be even more powerful
works 24 by7 if you give it a MacBook
mini or something or whatever.
So it will be great for entrepreneurs.
It'll be great for you know lean
startups. It will be disastrous for the
monolithic ancient outdated Indian
software industry IT industry. That's
how I see it going.
Hanish Sharma says Sergio Gore was in
western command and apparently the
higher command is not happy with the
person who approved the visit but it
looks wishy how could anyone even allow
this while we at a paused war look I
don't know but apparently who's happy or
unhappy I don't know about this to know
this you would have to be in the
echelons of power which I am not
so yeah Sergio G did visit the the
western command US military the
officials did visit.
Um I'm not sure who approved the visit.
I'm not sure who's happy, who's not. I
don't think it was a good thing that we
allowed this to happen. Give access to a
US ambassador to our western command. I
don't think it's the right thing for
India to do. It sends a very bad message
to the world, to the people of India. It
it sends vas wasal vibes to the world
which is not good because we are still
not vasals yet at least at any case. Uh
so yeah it was disappointing for me.
Pratitumar Roy says about the book
concepts of physics by Etsy WMA. I
haven't read that book. Uh Etsy Verma is
the is I believe at the same level as
resting and holiday right? Resting and
holiday is somewhere up here. I have
never studied HCMA. For me, it's resting
and holiday. If you ever want to go back
to the very basics of physics, you know,
college level physics, high school level
physics, you know, brush up your
concepts, holiday and resting is the way
to go. I don't know about it, so I can't
say.
Vihank Kuran says as we have seen
success and effectiveness of air defense
systems is it possible that using AI to
build an air defense system effective
against MI missiles and MI themselves
you use AI to do the decision-m and
controlling of the assets but building
the air defense system is a physical
process
so the AI can be the command and control
center and the brain of your air defense
systems
are hardware They are not software right
so you what you can do is you can have
multiple batteries of let's say Akash
missiles all connected coordinated with
a single AI system maybe a decentralized
AI system or some something a redundancy
given AI system and the AI system is
given eyes in the of what kind of eyes
the battle space awareness that comes
from the integrated battle battle space
awareness u uh network which is multiple
radars and Awax and whatnot all of that
creates an integrated picture of the
battle space and that way you can see
what's coming and let's say there's a
ballistic missile coming in and it
releases this MI thing so multiple
independently uh you know targetable
warheads and that gives you very short
reaction time but if you have a realtime
view of what's happening then an AI
system could potentially take out all of
those warheads so yeah AI gives you
these superpowers and that's why India
needs to have indigenous AI sovereign AI
and we are making baby steps in the
taking baby steps in the direction but
it's it's something India really needs
to have u yeah so it is definitely
possible to do what you're saying using
AI as a brain
time space theory why counting similar
to Indian shell counting um I don't know
about mech counting I can tell you who
themes are themes are this mysterious
vanished civilization in Miso America
all they left behind was this gigantic
ic stone heads. And if you look at the
facial features of the stone heads, they
look like people of African origin.
Let's see. I'll show you. Okay,
I'll make uh heads
there. We have it.
Colossal heads. And as you can see, the
facial features resemble people of
African origin, right?
They don't look very Miso American. I
mean, they don't look like the people
who live in Miso America today. Mis
America is Central America, right? So
the Olme heads uh Mexico's Gulf Coast
and so on. Now I am not aware of what
kind of counting system they had and
it's it's certainly possible that
you know two distinct civilizations
could eventually come up with a very
similar way of counting things. It's
possible.
I mean clearly the India and Miso
America are separated by more than
10,000 kilometers and these make heads
like are like what 3,000 years old or
something
um yeah about 3,000 plus years old.
So it's highly I mean it's not
impossible that India and Miso America
did not have any connections but uh
unlikely.
So most likely coincidence but who knows
who knows.
Died with precaution says your opinion
on the Golodia Golgotia incident in the
AI summit. I gave my opinion. I spoke
about it in detail so no point repeating
myself. Uh once the live stream is over
you can you can revisit that. Uh overall
it's it's terrible. Yeah. And it's it's
a symptom of the rotten education system
of India. The rotten and corrupt
education system of India. Terrible.
Terrible.
Really now Miss Patel says are we trying
to do a China hoping US would aid our
rise? Surely it won't happen a second
time right also we should learn some
stealing from the Chinese too. You know
what there's a lot we can learn from the
Chinese. There is a lot to admire about
what China has achieved and the way they
have gone about doing that. And the
Chinese
played the US. The Chinese did not pray
and hope the US would aid the rise. They
engineered things in such a way that the
US needed to aid China's rise.
Right? Because the Chinese had something
very substantial to offer the US. But
that was the 20th century and early 21st
century. The times have changed. Now the
US will not aid and abet the rise of
India. They won't do that.
Um so I don't think India is under the
illusion that the US will help us the
way the they help the Chinese. I don't
think the government of India is under
that illusion at all. The government of
India knows exactly what the US wants
from India. They want a vasal state. So
u the question essentially is what do we
do about this? We should do we resist or
do we just give in? That's uh a choice
the government of India is going to have
to make. Uh yeah and I agree we should
lead learn some stealing from the
Chinese too. Look in geopolitics there
are no rules. There is no right or
there's no wrong. There's no ethics and
morality.
It's perfectly fine to steal stuff in
geopolitics like the Chinese have done
like the Americans have also done. So if
everyone plays the game in with a
certain set of rules why should we have
a different set of rules for ourselves?
We should also play the game. So I agree
with you. Okay. Ritik Yaduanchi says
India is one of the oldest continuous
civilizations. No, India is the oldest
continuously existing civilization. It's
not one of the oldest. India is the
oldest continuously existing
civilization. Continuing, we have
ancient texts on music, art and
philosophy. Did we also have cookbooks
or recipe texts? What did people eat
back then? And did any have any of those
records survived? I can I I can tell you
about one cookbook. Okay. Um, it's not
merely a cookbook, but it has
culinary data in it. Manasa,
a book by Somaswara the third and uh,
Sumeshwara the third, the Chalukian
Emperor.
Once again reminding you the Wiki that
Wikipedia is not necessarily a reliable
source of information about Indian
history. The manas also known as Abilash
Abilash Shitamani
is a early 12th century Sanskrit text by
composed by Kalyani king Kalyani Chaluka
King Somish the third who lived in
present day Karnataka. Okay. And it is a
work covering topics such as polity,
governance, ethics, economics,
astronomy, astrology, rhetoric,
veterinary medicine, horiculture,
perfumes, food and so on and so forth.
So, it has information about what kind
of food our ancestors ate back in the
day. Now, let me see if I can open the
text. Uh, okay.
Uh, is this in Sanskrit? Is it in
English? This is the original Sanskrit
text. But I'm sure you can find the
Indian text also.
Okay, I'm not going to waste your time
trying to find the English version
of the text, but it's available online
and you can see that it has recipes,
you know, cook. It's kind of, you know,
it's got a section which is kind of like
a cookbook. It's got recipes in it. So,
you can find out for yourself what kind
of food our ancestors ate back in the
day. Some records have survived, a few.
Yeah. Cere serendipitously.
M 1169 says, "Can you upload book review
compilation video?" Yes, thank you for
the reminder. I need to do that. I've
done a whole bunch of book reviews which
are still stuck in those live streams. I
need to extract them and put them out
separately. I'll do that. Thank you.
Died with precaution says absolutely
right about coaching mafia. Even the
owner of my coaching used to say that
people who criticize Indian education
system are idiots and everything is
fine. Of course they'll say that they
their entire you know source of income
and wealth depends on the rotten corrupt
education system. So they'll say that
everything is fine. The truth is the
students know exactly how painful and
how horrible it is.
I mean some students understand most
students just just sleepwalk through
everything without ever understanding
how rotten the system is. So yeah, the
coaching mafia is is is a parasitical
entity that that leeches off the
lifeblood of of students and their
parents.
And the new education policy 2020 or
whatever the hell it is, does it address
this issue?
Does it address any of the major iss
etc. should be introduced early in the
education curriculum rather than only in
high higher education. In my opinion,
in basic education,
you should learn language, critical
thinking and arithmetic.
That's it.
Language means communication, verbal and
written communication
in your mother tongue and in the
civilizational language. Only two
languages, not no foreign language. If
someone wants to learn foreign
languages, they can learn in their own
free time. No question, no problem with
it. But the education system should be
in the mother tongue and it should teach
the civilizational language,
civilizational language, nothing else.
Two languages. So you should learn
communication which is verbal and
written. Secondly, you should learn
critical thinking, how to how to discern
what's right from what's wrong and so
on, decision- making, all of that
maybe national interest, what it is. And
thirdly, you should be taught
arithmetic,
multiplica, addition, subtraction,
multiplication, division and interest,
compound interest, all that stuff and
maybe some history. That's all you
should learn in your basic education.
All the other stuff should be I mean
when it comes to research and all most
people don't want to do research why
should be they have to learn research.
Why they teach algebra at what 8th?
9th00. Who who uses algebra in life?
They teach trigonometry. They teach
calculus.
Once you are out of school, do you ever
use calculus?
And I'm saying this as somebody who
loves high higher mathematics.
You don't need all that. So I would say
you don't need to do any research,
publications, etc. when you're in
school. Absolutely not. Just teach the
basics and stop wasting people's time.
Why do you have to spend 20 years in the
education system? You should be able to
become an intern or an apprentice in in
in in an industry by the age of 15 or
16. That's what I believe.
Dhir Kamat says, I don't completely
completely agree with your take on the
Indian education system. These days in
the US, there's a pandemic of high
school students who are unable to
perform basic algebra and cannot read at
even middle school level. I think other
than the Abrahamic history brainwashing
India's school system somewhat
effective. Having gone to a CBS school,
I found myself at an advantage in my
engineering program at top tier IV
adjacent university. All right, sir. I'm
glad it worked out for you. I believe
the Indian education system is rotten to
the core and you don't have to agree
with me. That's fine. That's fine. Um
maybe it turned out okay for you.
But it could have turned out
stupendously well for you, right? And
you obviously are someone who left India
and went to the US and studied there and
what you studied in India, whatever
preparatory work you did kind of helped
you to a certain extent. Okay, fine.
Good. Good for you. But I'm talking
about the education system as a tool of
India civilization revival.
Right? Do you understand? It may be okay
for you at from a personal perspective.
I am talking about the education system
as a tool for creating highquality
individuals
to raise the standards of the Indian
population
right it's somewhat effective who wants
godamn somewhat effective I want the
best education system in the world I
don't want a somewhat effective
education system so that's my
perspective sir
Han Sharma says it might come as a weird
question but is it normal to abuse when
we with friends. Did our ancestors do
it? And allow me to ask this. Do you
abuse when you get frustrated? Sorry if
it's a weird one. Uh, is it normal to
abuse when we with friends? I think it's
pretty common. I think it's pretty
common. Did our ancestors do it? Well, I
don't know if our ancestors did it or
not, but in the Sanskrit language, there
are plenty of words that are not very
nice.
I will not give you the words.
I know of a certain Russian word which
is used when you're frustrated and
you're very upset which has a direct
root in Sanskrit.
It's a word you use com you commonly
hear in Russian videos when people are
frustrated.
So, look, I'm pretty sure that it was
pretty common even in the past for
people to uh use u naughty words, gross
words or whatever. It's a it's okay.
It's no big deal. Do I do it? Well,
that's for that's for me to know.
Uh Brown Leprechaun has become a new
member. Thank you very much, sir. Thank
you very much. Welcome to the channel's
membership. Thank you.
Shivar Ali says, "Any update on American
history podcast?"
Well, no update right now. No update. No
progress on that front right now. I'm
not sure what happens with that podcast.
It's currently on in cold storage. It's
not dead.
It's a great project, but I have plenty
of projects to work on and I'm not sure
I can do all of those things at the same
time. So, right now, it's in cold
storage for now. Okay. And and thank you
very much for, you know, asking about
it. I'm glad that some people were
interested in that.
Okay. Brown Leprechaun again is a
member. Thank you very much. Um, Lit Paw
says India could have got independence
in 1920 or 1947. Well, if Shri Muandas
Gandhi had given a clarion call in 1920,
first of all, you know, Mr. Gandhi used
to tell the people of India,
non-ooperation with the British. Don't
do violence, do non-ooperation.
Why did he not tell the
police and military to do
non-ooperation?
He only told the civilians of India to
do non-ooperation with the British. He
never
told the police and the military to stop
cooperating with the British because if
you do that the British Empire is over.
So we could have got independence in
1920 itself and in 1920 if Mr. Gandhi
had given the order to all Indians.
Go out, go out of your house today
morning, tomorrow morning, find one
British person and kill him. One evil
foreign occupier of India and kill only
one person and go back home. By the end
of day, there would not be a single
British person alive in India. Yeah,
sure Indians would have died, but India
would have been free.
Freedom is not free. Maybe tens of
thousands of Indians would have died but
India would have become free within 24
hours. India could have become
independent with the right leadership.
We had the wrong leadership.
Seizure says don't you sometime
somewhere think the American military
power is an illusion or just showcase if
they fall in anarchy what's the point of
being a superpower? That's why you don't
fall into anarchy.
The American military power is not an
illusion. It's very real. Showcase are
you kidding me? They have flattened
entire nations.
One American submarine has the has the
capability to destroy an entire nation.
There's no illusion here. There's no
showcase stuff over here.
There's nothing. It's not It's not only
for show. It's very real power. Those
two those 800 extra territorial military
bases are not for show.
And they're not falling into anarchy.
They have issues. Sure. Every nation has
issues. So diet with precaution says how
about teaching AutoCAD and Photoshop in
education? You mean me? I don't know
AutoCAD. I am hardly a beginner in
Photoshop. So not for me. But but in the
education system. Yeah. Teach skills.
Teach skills.
There's nothing wrong with teaching
skills. So this can be a component of
education in the education system. For
sure. Yeah.
Okay. That brings me to the end finally
after three and a half hours of this
live stream. So, thank you very much
everybody. Thank you very much for
asking all these questions. And I shall
end this live stream over here tonight.
It's what 11:30 India time. That's
pretty late. So, let's end it over here.
Thank you very much everybody. And the
next live stream episode 333 is on
Monday evening India time. 8:00 p.m. Not
Sunday evening because there's a cricket
match and everybody will watch that and
I'll be sitting here doing the thing.
So, I'll see you Monday evening. Thank
you very much. Thank you very much
everybody. Take care. Keep asking
questions. Keep raising your standards.
See you very soon. Obate.